<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[Abhishek Sah]]></title><description><![CDATA[Portfolio website hosting mostly blogs, thoughts & ideas]]></description><link>http://abhisheksah.xyz</link><generator>GatsbyJS</generator><lastBuildDate>Sat, 11 Sep 2021 13:03:41 GMT</lastBuildDate><item><title><![CDATA[Horizontally scaling up a Kafka cluster ]]></title><description><![CDATA[I work in the Data Engineering team in Gojek, and my work involves managing lots of Kafka clusters, among other kinds of stuff. This blog is…]]></description><link>http://abhisheksah.xyz/kafka-scaling/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">http://abhisheksah.xyz/kafka-scaling/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 11 Sep 2021 22:12:03 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;I work in the Data Engineering team in Gojek, and my work involves managing lots of Kafka clusters, among other kinds of stuff. This blog is inspired by a recent outage in one of our Kafka cluster, causing degradation in the consumer applications. As a resort, we had to scale up the Kafka cluster horizontally. This blog will acquaint you with horizontally scaling up a Kafka cluster, spotlighting partition reassignment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Due to a high load on the cluster, we were facing high CPU on few brokers. We had an option to either increase the computing power on each broker simply by replacing them with powerful machines, i.e. vertical scaling. Vertically scaling a Kafka cluster means replacing existing broker nodes with higher capacity nodes while keeping the same brokers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But there are a few challenges when you do that. For example, it involves careful re-consideration of the broker configs to use the new compute power optimally. Over-provisioning of computing and storage resources to the cluster can be quite costly to the business. We didn’t want to put much effort into recalibrating our broker configurations as per new machine specs to save some time in a critical production support issue. So we decide to go for horizontally scaling the Kafka cluster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our Kafka brokers are usually standard Google Compute Engine instances. The broker configurations are defined in reusable IaC modules so that many teams can benefit from these well-thought configurations. All you need to do is provision your brokers using the IaC tool. In the Data Engineering team, we heavily use Terraform for IaC provisioning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Process&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Horizontally scaling the Kafka cluster involves these rough steps:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create new machines provisioning storage, networking, and compute resources&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Start the brokers with your chosen configurations and provisioned resources&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reassign partitions across the cluster so that the new brokers share the load and the cluster’s overall performance improves&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Steps 1 and 2 can be challenging, time-consuming, error-prone and tricky when you don’t have a standard way of creating new machines and provisioning them with necessary software and configurations. The Data Engineering team has diligently put lots of effort into achieving these standards across any deployment landscape, be it containers or virtual machines. It gives us exponential benefits saving a lot of time, avoiding configuration drift and human errors. So here, the only thing left to figure out was &lt;em&gt;reassignment of partitions&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before scaling up, the cluster had six brokers and ~1600 topics. As you might know, Kafka topics are further split into partitions to load balance. Brokers store these partitions. Brokers replicate partitions as per the replication configuration. If you are interested in a refresher, I’ve written about these concepts &lt;a href=&quot;https://abhisheksah.xyz/what-makes-kafka-awesome/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. When you add new brokers, you also need to manually rearrange the partitions across the cluster so that the new brokers can balance the load evenly across all brokers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For each partition of a topic, one broker gets elected as leader of that partition, and a few brokers participate in replicating that partition. So, for example: for a Topic T with replication factor 3, a partition Pi is distributed among Broker 1 as leader and Broker 2 and 3 as followers. When you run reassignment on this topic, leaders and followers will get modified.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s see a detailed example. The image below shows a topic &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;test-topic&lt;/code&gt; with 12 partitions and a storage plan across nine brokers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
      class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-wrapper&quot;
      style=&quot;position: relative; display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;  max-width: 319px;&quot;
    &gt;
      &lt;a
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-link&quot;
    href=&quot;/static/c594a1422f5ed095d1fe246ce0407d75/b53cf/before_reassignment.png&quot;
    style=&quot;display: block&quot;
    target=&quot;_blank&quot;
    rel=&quot;noopener&quot;
  &gt;
    &lt;span
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-background-image&quot;
    style=&quot;padding-bottom: 114.1891891891892%; position: relative; bottom: 0; left: 0; background-image: url(&apos;data:image/png;base64,iVBORw0KGgoAAAANSUhEUgAAABQAAAAXCAYAAAALHW+jAAAACXBIWXMAAAsSAAALEgHS3X78AAACMklEQVQ4y42Vxw7jMAxEnd577733IIcc8v+/xcXjQoItW9g9EApEasgZ0kyw2+0Em81mkk6nJQgCqVarUqvV9JzP5/J4POR0Oslms5Hn8ym3201/1+v1mAU43++3XC4XaTabUiwWJZ/PqwFeKpVktVrJaDTSB8vlUhaLhbRaLfXHbLvdavbhcCjr9Vr2+71cr1f9nfjg3xZIv99XELJDnYqgBOVGoyGHw0E+n49Sz2QyGvP9fjU5lZ/PZxmPx38Bs9ms5HI5GQwG0uv1pNPp6EnFhUJBbTKZyHQ61ROduYM2cSQEzEpAAHqVy2U9CTYnASRDRxJzn0ql9I6mcQ8LtMVvKUMR2kmacE8V4bt2u610qQw/PbCAZCQbFn7EPSdSGJ+5QxZAAEZD9KdqWyHj4lZhDN10vhzA4/FotWbkLCBBCGoeuQYtF5B4xo1kgDL8Zm4Do4lvUOmu8RlA4hkhGkLC+/2u4xShjPkoJwFCGX3xAxjpcrfb9WrII5cy8dDExxnR0GT0AXLPvIUB0Y1Pk4YAGOsyDh9lOopWboVm2zA2LJgIZYaTKpMAqSaJMoAUYb7lyNhAqVKpJAKGRyoMyA7FR0KWR4wyQf9bITIACCvGhq8mAkjrfRoC6H564bHBz5DHBhtQH6DbFOKpEGaAslwsIEHo9/v9wtNujWVqqg8Dvl4vfUdTzOK1FSIuOvjGxqVM1awvZpDqALcagswMuevLGD4DZIxlTHUsYX5TsfnH/AOnrQ60HGDyTwAAAABJRU5ErkJggg==&apos;); background-size: cover; display: block;&quot;
  &gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;img
        class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-image&quot;
        alt=&quot;Before Reassignment&quot;
        title=&quot;Before Reassignment&quot;
        src=&quot;/static/c594a1422f5ed095d1fe246ce0407d75/b53cf/before_reassignment.png&quot;
        srcset=&quot;/static/c594a1422f5ed095d1fe246ce0407d75/12f09/before_reassignment.png 148w,
/static/c594a1422f5ed095d1fe246ce0407d75/e4a3f/before_reassignment.png 295w,
/static/c594a1422f5ed095d1fe246ce0407d75/b53cf/before_reassignment.png 319w&quot;
        sizes=&quot;(max-width: 319px) 100vw, 319px&quot;
        style=&quot;width:100%;height:100%;margin:0;vertical-align:middle;position:absolute;top:0;left:0;&quot;
        loading=&quot;lazy&quot;
      /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;After running partition reassignment:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
      class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-wrapper&quot;
      style=&quot;position: relative; display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;  max-width: 319px;&quot;
    &gt;
      &lt;a
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-link&quot;
    href=&quot;/static/4bac8ceb2c069dc204f5714c5b4114cb/b53cf/after_reassignment.png&quot;
    style=&quot;display: block&quot;
    target=&quot;_blank&quot;
    rel=&quot;noopener&quot;
  &gt;
    &lt;span
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-background-image&quot;
    style=&quot;padding-bottom: 114.1891891891892%; position: relative; bottom: 0; left: 0; background-image: url(&apos;data:image/png;base64,iVBORw0KGgoAAAANSUhEUgAAABQAAAAXCAYAAAALHW+jAAAACXBIWXMAAAsSAAALEgHS3X78AAACQElEQVQ4y3WV567qMBCEEzqEehJq6O0EuFSJIiHx/m+1N5+PHBEn+bEycZmd3Rkbq1KpSD6fV2HbtliWFY1ELpdTodf1b0a9Jxb3+13e77ecTqfUDaPRSJ7Pp+x2O/F9Xx6Ph1wuF5lOp+mA+/1elsulzGYzdXgymchisRDP81IPwC4VSEe73ZYgCBTIeDyW1Wolm81GAVNWqVSScrks9XpdBYeazaY0Gg0V1WpV7SkWixrUUmwoGZYE5fDNJtd15Xq9yuv1ktvtppJQ+ufzEapjL/OQiQAJMjmOo4LMtVpNiUCJMONbzxHsR1BCs4wAydhqtSKFtZqaPYe04oydTkd6vZ4ah8Oh0uCrj5aiTV+yVIbB9xwg8/lcJaNUwyGWIAyNTwOkp1oMHbADCIasY6kYYLfbTRzSgSi6ZB39fl+5AmDO4pIYIAuIkQY4GAwSgMxhL5LxG7VjgPQCZdMAabjJXgNyjl5iqwTDrJIxuJkMUTC/FuV4PCZ7mFUya4VCIcEQIABJeDgc4oBsyAJEANMB7EcUkqHy+XyOA9KHrB5miUJv8S/W2W63SR+a5v0+zJUz59brtSJB6QmGUM8CzCqZqmDHmLgp9IHFNEDueVrJ+rlLvSksmGV9W8RkD2tKxtisJwDJyLP+N2HHRt8nmRObAwRj/91pbPPP7KEXXp8gw9h+2Py4pYaDkOFqKZ77E67z2hjGdt2+TGcAVsTOOWHU1Mh358eXUpm3shrNjUbh38T2HPYvENebyG9widb/AyKlC9X9ztUeAAAAAElFTkSuQmCC&apos;); background-size: cover; display: block;&quot;
  &gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;img
        class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-image&quot;
        alt=&quot;After Reassignment&quot;
        title=&quot;After Reassignment&quot;
        src=&quot;/static/4bac8ceb2c069dc204f5714c5b4114cb/b53cf/after_reassignment.png&quot;
        srcset=&quot;/static/4bac8ceb2c069dc204f5714c5b4114cb/12f09/after_reassignment.png 148w,
/static/4bac8ceb2c069dc204f5714c5b4114cb/e4a3f/after_reassignment.png 295w,
/static/4bac8ceb2c069dc204f5714c5b4114cb/b53cf/after_reassignment.png 319w&quot;
        sizes=&quot;(max-width: 319px) 100vw, 319px&quot;
        style=&quot;width:100%;height:100%;margin:0;vertical-align:middle;position:absolute;top:0;left:0;&quot;
        loading=&quot;lazy&quot;
      /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you can see, the Kafka controller node readjusted the partitions storage to different brokers. Initially, the Kafka controller node stored Partition 0 on brokers 3, 4 and 5, with 4th as the leader. After the reassignment, it got stored on 1, 5 and 9 with the 5th broker as the leader.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When adding new brokers, the partition reassignment will ensure that the partitions of topics are balanced across the brokers, including the ones we added as part of scaling. We need to do this on all the topics for optimal load balance across newly added brokers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Execution&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now let’s have a quick look at how to go about doing the reassignment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The standard Kafka installation has the required script to run the reassignment. It can be found as &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;bin/kafka-reassign-partitions.sh&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reassignment is a 3 step process:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;First, we put the list of topics we want to load balance in a JSON file.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;json&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;language-json&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-json&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token property&quot;&gt;&quot;topics&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;token property&quot;&gt;&quot;topic&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&quot;test-topic&quot;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token property&quot;&gt;&quot;version&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;ol start=&quot;2&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We tell the Kafka cluster to generate a plan for us. It will log to console, the current partition replica assignment and proposed partition reassignment configuration&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;sh&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;language-sh&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-sh&quot;&gt;bin/kafka-reassign-partitions.sh \
--bootstrap-server &amp;quot;my-kafka.example.com&amp;quot; \
--broker-list &amp;quot;1,2,3,4,5,6,7,8,9&amp;quot; \
--topics-to-move-json-file &amp;quot;/root/topics.json&amp;quot; \
--zookeeper &amp;quot;my-zookeper.example.com&amp;quot; \
--generate&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Put the proposed partition reassignment configuration in a JSON file.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&quot;3&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We execute the assignment on the proposed plan.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;sh&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;language-sh&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-sh&quot;&gt;bin/kafka-reassign-partitions.sh \
--bootstrap-server &amp;quot;my-kafka.example.com&amp;quot; \
--reassignment-json-file &amp;quot;/root/plan.json&amp;quot; \
--zookeeper &amp;quot;my-zookeper.example.com&amp;quot; \
--execute&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The execution time depends on the size of the topic, and it happens asynchronously. You can query the state of this execution by verifying.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;sh&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;language-sh&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-sh&quot;&gt;bin/kafka-reassign-partitions.sh \
--bootstrap-server &amp;quot;my-kafka.example.com&amp;quot; \
--reassignment-json-file &amp;quot;/root/plan.json&amp;quot; \
--zookeeper &amp;quot;my-zookeper.example.com&amp;quot; \
--verify&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Next steps&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Doing partition reassignment &lt;em&gt;manually&lt;/em&gt; for a big cluster having thousands of topics is time-consuming. As a next step, we are looking to develop automation to do the partition reassignment with minimal intervention.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[What makes Kafka awesome?]]></title><description><![CDATA[Kafka is one of those software that are in the foundations of most of the data-driven companies e.g. LinkedIn, Uber, Spotify, Slack, Gojek…]]></description><link>http://abhisheksah.xyz/what-makes-kafka-awesome/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">http://abhisheksah.xyz/what-makes-kafka-awesome/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 07 May 2020 22:12:03 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://kafka.apache.org/&quot;&gt;Kafka&lt;/a&gt; is one of those software that are in the foundations of most of the data-driven companies e.g. LinkedIn, Uber, Spotify, Slack, Gojek etc. Kafka solves the problem of high throughput real-time data streaming with minimal latency. It’s flexible and lean architecture has helped companies scale massively without worrying about the quality and latency of the data pipeline. In this blog, we will go through internals of mighty Kafka and will find out what makes Kafka so awesome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s begin with a subtle introduction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What is Kafka&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kafka is a distributed streaming platform. To quote from the official website,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A streaming platform has three key capabilities:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Publish and subscribe to streams of records, similar to a message queue or enterprise messaging system.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Store streams of records in a fault-tolerant durable way.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Process streams of records as they occur.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kafka is used to build data pipelines, to move data among systems or applications. Kafka can store the data as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By “data”, we mean any form of raw data or event that needs to be sent across applications or services. For example, user activity events(page views, button clicks, logins, sign ups, likes, comments etc.) or operational metrics such as errors in applications, crashes, system usage etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These raw events are produced by users via their interaction with applications and kafka pipelines can be used to send(stream) them at desired places(applications/services). The consuming applications or services can decide to process this raw data in real time or store it for later processing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why do we need to stream these raw data/events in the first place?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because this helps data-driven companies make efficient decisions. Companies can use this data to develop internal applications and microservices to improve their search relevance, recommendation systems, and target appropriate ads to customers etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the use cases grow and companies scale, the user facing applications produce more and more data. Streaming that data to various internal applications and services without compromising scale is the one of the onus of data engineering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This data can be of enormous volume. Think of the scale at which social media giants like Facebook, LinkedIn operate and storing all major events done by users on their website and mobile applications. This becomes billions of events every day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Streaming such enormous amount of data maintaining minimum latency is no simple job. Kafka is very good at this(we will see how). Moreover, Kafka gives you the ability to perform processing on the stream. One example of such real-time processing is calculating &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.davemanuel.com/investor-dictionary/surge-pricing/&quot;&gt;surge pricing&lt;/a&gt; in apps(like Uber).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Surge pricing is calculated by taking into consideration the current demand and current supply. These two metrics are used in real-time to calculate how much surge price to add to the trip. For example, Surge price in Uber during rains in the evening.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The real-time usage of log data brings several challenges. One of which is high throughput. Kafka gives the ability to perform such real-time processing with minimal latency. Kafka is scalable, distributed, supports high throughput, supports real-time consumption of data and provides a &lt;a href=&quot;https://kafka.apache.org/documentation/#api&quot;&gt;rich set of APIs&lt;/a&gt; to make developers life easy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Kafka Architecture&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kafka’s architecture is fairly simple. There are a few logical concepts that you need to understand in order to deep dive into Kafka. Kafka runs on &lt;a href=&quot;https://aws.amazon.com/pub-sub-messaging/&quot;&gt;Pub/Sub Model&lt;/a&gt;. Which means, there are entities which produce messages and put in some designated places and there are entities which subscribe to these places.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Topic:&lt;/strong&gt; Stream of messages of a particular type is called a topic. For example, a BookingLog Topic for Uber will keep all messages of trip booking type made on the Uber app.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Producer:&lt;/strong&gt; The entity which produces messages to a topic. The producer application constructs the messages and sends it to Kafka to store that message in a particular topic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Broker:&lt;/strong&gt; Brokers are servers where the published messages are stored.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Consumer:&lt;/strong&gt; The entity which consumes data that was put in a topic(from the Brokers). Consumers consume messages inside a topic from Broker via a bridge called Message Streams.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given these basic terminologies, you would have guessed the basic flow of data in Kafka.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Producers produce messages(data) in topics. Brokers store those data. Consumers can consume data from these topics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
      class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-wrapper&quot;
      style=&quot;position: relative; display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;  max-width: 590px;&quot;
    &gt;
      &lt;a
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-link&quot;
    href=&quot;/static/86628d1bd5c7b4c66bf5da5effb8d0b0/dd507/1.png&quot;
    style=&quot;display: block&quot;
    target=&quot;_blank&quot;
    rel=&quot;noopener&quot;
  &gt;
    &lt;span
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-background-image&quot;
    style=&quot;padding-bottom: 18.91891891891892%; position: relative; bottom: 0; left: 0; background-image: url(&apos;data:image/png;base64,iVBORw0KGgoAAAANSUhEUgAAABQAAAAECAIAAAABPYjBAAAACXBIWXMAAAsSAAALEgHS3X78AAAAuklEQVQI13WOzQqCQBSFfYgWrUIpgra9TpteLSinH6x0bfgKLYJsoY6CoUj+zIy/WNMoGW26fBzu4Z4Dl6PtvFo9P4qdgY8WOfxBMomX1U2+LXBRFCUIM6uH2WRrD1ZQECEPIC92gIYhgL2FOdc8Sp8kzTAheZ5zCCG20brSAzyVHAHAEYuuO8BHxxu7v7RmqluUZRzHYRgmScL9vm2gSnWzk4Nl3VOuvqz7ys3fX+7MMjQ3Zdcgr7/5N32Kwi2XMPMPAAAAAElFTkSuQmCC&apos;); background-size: cover; display: block;&quot;
  &gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;img
        class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-image&quot;
        alt=&quot;Producer-Consumer&quot;
        title=&quot;Producer-Consumer&quot;
        src=&quot;/static/86628d1bd5c7b4c66bf5da5effb8d0b0/fcda8/1.png&quot;
        srcset=&quot;/static/86628d1bd5c7b4c66bf5da5effb8d0b0/12f09/1.png 148w,
/static/86628d1bd5c7b4c66bf5da5effb8d0b0/e4a3f/1.png 295w,
/static/86628d1bd5c7b4c66bf5da5effb8d0b0/fcda8/1.png 590w,
/static/86628d1bd5c7b4c66bf5da5effb8d0b0/efc66/1.png 885w,
/static/86628d1bd5c7b4c66bf5da5effb8d0b0/c83ae/1.png 1180w,
/static/86628d1bd5c7b4c66bf5da5effb8d0b0/dd507/1.png 1528w&quot;
        sizes=&quot;(max-width: 590px) 100vw, 590px&quot;
        style=&quot;width:100%;height:100%;margin:0;vertical-align:middle;position:absolute;top:0;left:0;&quot;
        loading=&quot;lazy&quot;
      /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Topics can be of very high throughput depending on the use cases. BookingsLog alone is a very high throughput topic if you think about Uber’s scale. So to balance the load, topics are further divided into Partitions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
      class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-wrapper&quot;
      style=&quot;position: relative; display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;  max-width: 586px;&quot;
    &gt;
      &lt;a
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-link&quot;
    href=&quot;/static/2769fcc22eb4e863ad7225e9dfe04ed5/a76f4/2.png&quot;
    style=&quot;display: block&quot;
    target=&quot;_blank&quot;
    rel=&quot;noopener&quot;
  &gt;
    &lt;span
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-background-image&quot;
    style=&quot;padding-bottom: 90.54054054054053%; position: relative; bottom: 0; left: 0; background-image: url(&apos;data:image/png;base64,iVBORw0KGgoAAAANSUhEUgAAABQAAAASCAIAAADUsmlHAAAACXBIWXMAAAsSAAALEgHS3X78AAACHUlEQVQ4y52US08TURTH5xOY6EJjsUVi8FUlMepC4+s76MpvYCSNG12pJLpQWfgJXIB2ppQKppi4ML4SQIhQUSriRDpPKsO8q7TTed3rGfoaUUPD5Lc48z/33HvPmX+GwFt6fIwRxgREOaV6e1a71R43Z7S+WY02HSgkZMs7lRV3PWGiJLtnM2IUu32gcH1ahUqEMPHVsLso7mCajw/zhzfjSIaPkewg/ROKPYSCa9/9qB8bEU4+E09sYFQICCmwpmdEuPRqpVj2cK1naF21PKnira4jlV2ligqy+S6Xn6EZTvslW/5qIytXvOU1F9bXi20ffS85i4bzrQ1ow8lrNuxSL4YB7E9zbfa8L8VdfLki1Yq/6HYnxcUz/NFMkAsD24EeDyk9T/kuiqWWGgPTq/6F58s7HzORJLs7RITkokNiNCVA0BQ7SHbbQKF3UobvFHwq2GPBsPs/6fdD9M+bfVPFxIuFG2+W7nyQHnw2mql7wJxeN8l/HYhcvKZiB27o/sOeqGHPt8XK1Ql5A72TSmJaT0xpELTECfnKuHztvUKbdnDyj7J7fFSMJJlOKnBfGDAsECNbyt4Uu2OwAN6uHU7A7buH+O40Dw498Cd/K4eG+Y4k+2ix1LLnw3njzJgIMz8f4mxWAM6NiUBThDWns+Ll1xKYrDUw0/YVy1PXUSqubiNeLY3P5XM0AwG8gljLapYHncpNe3poa38E/BuB2D/72m7hNQAAAABJRU5ErkJggg==&apos;); background-size: cover; display: block;&quot;
  &gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;img
        class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-image&quot;
        alt=&quot;Partition&quot;
        title=&quot;Partition&quot;
        src=&quot;/static/2769fcc22eb4e863ad7225e9dfe04ed5/a76f4/2.png&quot;
        srcset=&quot;/static/2769fcc22eb4e863ad7225e9dfe04ed5/12f09/2.png 148w,
/static/2769fcc22eb4e863ad7225e9dfe04ed5/e4a3f/2.png 295w,
/static/2769fcc22eb4e863ad7225e9dfe04ed5/a76f4/2.png 586w&quot;
        sizes=&quot;(max-width: 586px) 100vw, 586px&quot;
        style=&quot;width:100%;height:100%;margin:0;vertical-align:middle;position:absolute;top:0;left:0;&quot;
        loading=&quot;lazy&quot;
      /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each broker stores one or more partitions of various topics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
      class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-wrapper&quot;
      style=&quot;position: relative; display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;  max-width: 590px;&quot;
    &gt;
      &lt;a
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-link&quot;
    href=&quot;/static/a4928c83ae4cfed322b03f1484bae121/29007/3.png&quot;
    style=&quot;display: block&quot;
    target=&quot;_blank&quot;
    rel=&quot;noopener&quot;
  &gt;
    &lt;span
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-background-image&quot;
    style=&quot;padding-bottom: 41.21621621621622%; position: relative; bottom: 0; left: 0; background-image: url(&apos;data:image/png;base64,iVBORw0KGgoAAAANSUhEUgAAABQAAAAICAIAAAB2/0i6AAAACXBIWXMAAAsSAAALEgHS3X78AAABV0lEQVQY03VRz0sCQRjdv6C7RaduQp07BknHDlLQqUOXOgSeu3fv0LmCNDKlHxCu0A8UDKFTEkUQrqtW47qrTjntujszzvbNeinMx2Pgm29mvvfeKIwxypg3RNikAfgIwEUF2v4IUE9CCF8MQXYpVVxKb1EvpZEz/Rt4GqxQ5lDP9eT4f9/lwoemomEnnK6FEvpEohI61Mbj2mSiMnagxYoWnGnb3tZ9ay1vrBfMATcK5mrO2H36BN0KSM8jJ1kmRy/tvRLaL6H4s3VSJtm67VHaJO58BoVT9el0NZysAGdS+tRxNVZs9TlTPrpu9NqYu3yPZFBEbURUtKCi2fO37Qfs8yCzvm9zH9uugbsG/moR22aCMCFlN0lv885cuWksZ2uLF6/AJVWPXqGdR8yCxAKP4q9lWcq0+5wLIZMHD7jTsUwTxoEkh1IX8voFEGFZluM4g38C/AD12KTyT3EBAAAAAABJRU5ErkJggg==&apos;); background-size: cover; display: block;&quot;
  &gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;img
        class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-image&quot;
        alt=&quot;Topic BookingLog split into 3 partitions &amp;amp; stored on 2 brokers.&quot;
        title=&quot;Topic BookingLog split into 3 partitions &amp;amp; stored on 2 brokers.&quot;
        src=&quot;/static/a4928c83ae4cfed322b03f1484bae121/fcda8/3.png&quot;
        srcset=&quot;/static/a4928c83ae4cfed322b03f1484bae121/12f09/3.png 148w,
/static/a4928c83ae4cfed322b03f1484bae121/e4a3f/3.png 295w,
/static/a4928c83ae4cfed322b03f1484bae121/fcda8/3.png 590w,
/static/a4928c83ae4cfed322b03f1484bae121/efc66/3.png 885w,
/static/a4928c83ae4cfed322b03f1484bae121/c83ae/3.png 1180w,
/static/a4928c83ae4cfed322b03f1484bae121/29007/3.png 1600w&quot;
        sizes=&quot;(max-width: 590px) 100vw, 590px&quot;
        style=&quot;width:100%;height:100%;margin:0;vertical-align:middle;position:absolute;top:0;left:0;&quot;
        loading=&quot;lazy&quot;
      /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Partitions of a topic are simply Log files. Think of all the partitions of a topic as a file on the storage system of the Brokers. Depending on the usage, this partition’s(Log file’s) size can vary. It can be very large for some high throughput topics. So it is &lt;a href=&quot;http://man7.org/linux/man-pages/man1/split.1.html&quot;&gt;split&lt;/a&gt; into multiple smaller files, called &lt;strong&gt;Segment Files&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A partition now logically looks like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
      class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-wrapper&quot;
      style=&quot;position: relative; display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;  max-width: 590px;&quot;
    &gt;
      &lt;a
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-link&quot;
    href=&quot;/static/a9db5c497734c6f25476158324c2b5e8/29007/4.png&quot;
    style=&quot;display: block&quot;
    target=&quot;_blank&quot;
    rel=&quot;noopener&quot;
  &gt;
    &lt;span
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-background-image&quot;
    style=&quot;padding-bottom: 35.13513513513513%; position: relative; bottom: 0; left: 0; background-image: url(&apos;data:image/png;base64,iVBORw0KGgoAAAANSUhEUgAAABQAAAAHCAIAAACHqfpvAAAACXBIWXMAAAsSAAALEgHS3X78AAABfElEQVQY0x2QWU/CUBCF+6d98cHENTzof1AEAQlopQstlJ3S/XahhULZWlDBuGEUkkpwMLkP95tzZubci/X682hcSNzKybS83W4t+/Ey1oonpTscASrq5ComXN+IZN4CbPBe9EaEClfuAmI0ayM9WK/DyAWTuUcgm+3Zx+fPcYSimHal1ut7i/lieXCcK1XcAteZzd794G1vP9PtPWO8MGi2BvGkXG/2y1UXGUGDH8QSkqyOofkfvXhKNszpA2GoyK83vVRaFcQRGLCWOATT0RnJFB1BGmloghPG4SnZ5L1yzVW0cRZHJxFK032m4IjyKJ1VI+cMXAxrisEeURqBQ1LG0KCiCQiQ37JnLNdRdR/q2Xt9MHwhaEvRJoB4zrCdRxiHwTwy39bNgKDNUtWFQ7OQ1oc48Css53CVjqbvnsBVutBf5/saGmdwtNv88bliiyZBKcWSvfxav75904wOWKo6q3X4NF+StJajlGrdDX83fvBKUCqovOCF4eYPgcJLsqfHMiwAAAAASUVORK5CYII=&apos;); background-size: cover; display: block;&quot;
  &gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;img
        class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-image&quot;
        alt=&quot;Partition&quot;
        title=&quot;Partition&quot;
        src=&quot;/static/a9db5c497734c6f25476158324c2b5e8/fcda8/4.png&quot;
        srcset=&quot;/static/a9db5c497734c6f25476158324c2b5e8/12f09/4.png 148w,
/static/a9db5c497734c6f25476158324c2b5e8/e4a3f/4.png 295w,
/static/a9db5c497734c6f25476158324c2b5e8/fcda8/4.png 590w,
/static/a9db5c497734c6f25476158324c2b5e8/efc66/4.png 885w,
/static/a9db5c497734c6f25476158324c2b5e8/c83ae/4.png 1180w,
/static/a9db5c497734c6f25476158324c2b5e8/29007/4.png 1600w&quot;
        sizes=&quot;(max-width: 590px) 100vw, 590px&quot;
        style=&quot;width:100%;height:100%;margin:0;vertical-align:middle;position:absolute;top:0;left:0;&quot;
        loading=&quot;lazy&quot;
      /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Partition P2 split into 4 segment FilesLet’s say Partition P2 is the set of segment files S1, S2, S3 and S4. Any new message produced to Partition P2 will be written to the last segment file(here, say, S4).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is to be noted that, at first the segment file lives in the memory of a broker. After a predefined threshold is reached, then only the segment file is flushed to the disk i.e. written on the secondary storage. There are two such predefined thresholds:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A certain number of messages have been published from the publisher of that partition.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Certain time has elapsed since last published event.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The messages are only exposed to consumers when they are written to the disk. Messages residing in the memory of Brokers are never exposed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Message format&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every message in Kafka is stored with an offset. This is so because the messages can be of varying size. So offset is decided by the size of the messages in the segment files.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, Let’s say for segment file S1, three messages came from the producer which are of size 20bytes, 40 bytes and 20 bytes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then the ordering of message in segment file with offset typically looks like the image below with offset of M1 as 0, offset of M2 as 20 and offset of M3 as 40.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
      class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-wrapper&quot;
      style=&quot;position: relative; display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;  max-width: 590px;&quot;
    &gt;
      &lt;a
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-link&quot;
    href=&quot;/static/9f139a53e0efd7d5291462bf5344a922/d777c/5.png&quot;
    style=&quot;display: block&quot;
    target=&quot;_blank&quot;
    rel=&quot;noopener&quot;
  &gt;
    &lt;span
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-background-image&quot;
    style=&quot;padding-bottom: 27.027027027027025%; position: relative; bottom: 0; left: 0; background-image: url(&apos;data:image/png;base64,iVBORw0KGgoAAAANSUhEUgAAABQAAAAFCAIAAADKYVtkAAAACXBIWXMAAAsSAAALEgHS3X78AAAAj0lEQVQY012OUQ6EIBBDuf8BOYKJkPghgoCA+5ZGN9l+YKfTqTX3g+u6Sil6c85lotYqRSKoE5AxhnmPmfHFGHvv53m21ljjkwKXgZctWRh+x/iY932Hs8MtEkJ4DYhcEtcmDKkMRKIqWwd/tSEpJTlV8HvMx1q7rutxHKqKdVmW8UCd+TOlnHNq4b3ftu0DuWAkISWdWO8AAAAASUVORK5CYII=&apos;); background-size: cover; display: block;&quot;
  &gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;img
        class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-image&quot;
        alt=&quot;A typical order of messages inside a segment file.&quot;
        title=&quot;A typical order of messages inside a segment file.&quot;
        src=&quot;/static/9f139a53e0efd7d5291462bf5344a922/fcda8/5.png&quot;
        srcset=&quot;/static/9f139a53e0efd7d5291462bf5344a922/12f09/5.png 148w,
/static/9f139a53e0efd7d5291462bf5344a922/e4a3f/5.png 295w,
/static/9f139a53e0efd7d5291462bf5344a922/fcda8/5.png 590w,
/static/9f139a53e0efd7d5291462bf5344a922/efc66/5.png 885w,
/static/9f139a53e0efd7d5291462bf5344a922/c83ae/5.png 1180w,
/static/9f139a53e0efd7d5291462bf5344a922/d777c/5.png 1555w&quot;
        sizes=&quot;(max-width: 590px) 100vw, 590px&quot;
        style=&quot;width:100%;height:100%;margin:0;vertical-align:middle;position:absolute;top:0;left:0;&quot;
        loading=&quot;lazy&quot;
      /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here you can see the offsets are in increasing order but they are not consecutive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Traditionally, message queue systems (such as RabbitMQ) use message ID instead of offset. The message ID does the one-to-one mapping of Message’s location on disk. This allows the user to do random indexing of the messages. Random access to messages is a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.geeksforgeeks.org/difference-between-seek-time-and-rotational-latency-in-disk-scheduling/&quot;&gt;seek&lt;/a&gt; intensive operation. This is a costly IO operation affecting latency. Kafka avoids using message IDs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Offsets are also used as consumers acknowledgements. If a consumer acknowledges an offset x, it is assumed that the consumer has consumed all messages with offset &amp;#x3C; x.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Managing partitions on the broker&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s time to understand how brokers store and manage any partition. As we have understood, partitions are a set of segment files. Every segment file starts with some message. Every message is identified with a message offset.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Brokers store a sorted table in memory which basically keeps the first offset of each segment file.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s see it this way. Let’s say for partition P1, there are 5 segment files(S1, S2, S3, S4 and S5). The first message in S1 has offset 0. Likewise, first messages of files S2, S3, S4 and S5 have offsets 1000, 2000, 2500 and 2700 respectively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
      class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-wrapper&quot;
      style=&quot;position: relative; display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;  max-width: 306px;&quot;
    &gt;
      &lt;a
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-link&quot;
    href=&quot;/static/79d1bd16b9ce30ab7ade56a2422aabb0/98b92/6.png&quot;
    style=&quot;display: block&quot;
    target=&quot;_blank&quot;
    rel=&quot;noopener&quot;
  &gt;
    &lt;span
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-background-image&quot;
    style=&quot;padding-bottom: 138.51351351351352%; position: relative; bottom: 0; left: 0; background-image: url(&apos;data:image/png;base64,iVBORw0KGgoAAAANSUhEUgAAABQAAAAcCAIAAADuuAg3AAAACXBIWXMAAAsSAAALEgHS3X78AAACL0lEQVQ4y42USY/aQBCF/f+FRACJU+CAOMEBInFCCCQOCMQqdgggCOuw70vY8uHOgI3tTN6hVe6qLr96XdVSKBRqt9v1ev2nHlqtlu5+o9FIp9NSs9m83++32+2uh+PxqN0UwfP5XOKfWJfL5abA9Xplc71eOxyO4XCIzc6bdzweS3AQPm3u0+kUDAaXy+UbNWFPJhOpUqmIuN8anM9n4ljf9gnmZzCSwuFwt9ul8pYaTRkII4w3Fxpns1kJt5Fgok4jwabTqY5gov5UKhWJRH7I8Pl8+/3+me4lmNHhfD7v9/tR+7uM7Xarc1hXbQGlclraD7Wj0Si6dTqdX2ogSecTfCoDsHu9XqFQkEqlEpkOh8NRjScXUYvSRTB0+v2+Dm3BqlqtohnpKT6XyymZv2jXajUsfFcF2HG5XHa73WazmUwms9lMqwpd8bL+FUz3nvmkNrT4kIGhpTabzaR4PM58jEajDzUWi8XsEwQoXQTDGcpSIpEgjq2xGhwQ5+cylC6CaS8aRIe2sEVGRoqThOrTNhLM7XajltPp/CZjtVq9CUZqQ8G4nmKxmEwmmZ5MJqO9qsefuczNZvOs7Qk6Ybfbse5lKF0EUw6DKcViMUoaDAZDNRhyelCsQBmADWdekX/NsxFetHUfQHZISmNSMAHlcplmfvb51yPp9XoDgYDH47FarRaLRcyzyPvqbaOnF6lFS9RlCLX/989f1vx4wyiMidFeFb5nb2Nrr4rX4g+3Axv3rYJ7XgAAAABJRU5ErkJggg==&apos;); background-size: cover; display: block;&quot;
  &gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;img
        class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-image&quot;
        alt=&quot;Broker&amp;#39;s in-memory table&quot;
        title=&quot;Broker&amp;#39;s in-memory table&quot;
        src=&quot;/static/79d1bd16b9ce30ab7ade56a2422aabb0/98b92/6.png&quot;
        srcset=&quot;/static/79d1bd16b9ce30ab7ade56a2422aabb0/12f09/6.png 148w,
/static/79d1bd16b9ce30ab7ade56a2422aabb0/e4a3f/6.png 295w,
/static/79d1bd16b9ce30ab7ade56a2422aabb0/98b92/6.png 306w&quot;
        sizes=&quot;(max-width: 306px) 100vw, 306px&quot;
        style=&quot;width:100%;height:100%;margin:0;vertical-align:middle;position:absolute;top:0;left:0;&quot;
        loading=&quot;lazy&quot;
      /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The broker will store an in-memory table which keeps the offset of the first message in each segment file. Here : 0, 1000, 2000, 2500, 2700&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Table of starting offset of each segment fileAny new message which comes, if stored in S5, won’t affect this table. As soon as, a new segment file appears, this table will be updated with the offset of the first message in the new segment file.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This table is used to find the segment file which contains the offset asked by the consumer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Consumption of messages&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consuming messages is fairly simple. The series of events are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Consumers send a pull request to brokers. In this request, there are two things: Consumers specify the &lt;em&gt;offset to begin with&lt;/em&gt;, and an &lt;em&gt;acceptable number of bytes in the message&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Broker on receiving the offset to begin calculates which segment file has the message with asked offset. Broker searches the above table for the address of the segment file to which the message belongs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Broker fetches the data from that segment file and sends to the consumer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The consumer consumes this data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The consumer sends the next offset in the new pull request.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Efficiency of Kafka&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kafka is considered the best real-time streaming platform out there. The efficiency speaks for itself in various benchmarking tests. This efficiency results from several design decisions(rather unconventional).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Storage Efficiency&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first one is the use of offsets instead of message-ids which saves the cost of seek intensive random accesses. On top of that, keeping an index of the offsets of starting message in each segment file makes consumption from a partition fairly efficient.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second unconventional choice that we see in Kafka is avoiding any caching in Kafka Layer. Kafka avoids caching every message in memory at the process level. Instead, it relies on the underlying file system cache. This offers multiple benefits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, it avoids double buffering. Modern operating heavily use main memory for disk caching. A modern OS will happily divert all free memory to disk caching with little performance penalty when the memory is reclaimed. All disk reads and writes will go through this unified cache. So even if a process maintains an in-process cache of the data, this data will likely be duplicated in OS page cache, effectively storing everything twice. Although there could be a debate on when and how to process level caching is useful. Read this &lt;a href=&quot;https://queue.acm.org/detail.cfm?id=1563874&quot;&gt;ACM article&lt;/a&gt; for a thorough analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Secondly, this cache(the file system cache) will stay warm even if the broker service is restarted, whereas the in-process cache will need to be rebuilt in memory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The third benefit is that no cache at process level means, less overhead in Garbage collection, giving efficiency in VM based languages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fourth benefit comes from the use of traditional caching heuristics like write-through cache. Since both consumer and producer access the segment files sequentially, normal caching heuristics present in most OS works fine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Network Efficiency&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consumption of messages from the File system involves fetching message from secondary storage and sending all the way to network sockets. This typically involves reading data from the storage to page cache, copying page cache to application buffer, copying application buffer to kernel buffer and finally sending kernel buffer to a socket. This involves 4 data copying calls and 2 system calls.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kafka uses the &lt;a href=&quot;http://man7.org/linux/man-pages/man2/sendfile.2.html&quot;&gt;sendfile API&lt;/a&gt; available in Linux which does the same thing in 2 data copying calls and 1 system call. This optimized API results in the fast consumption of data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Broker’s design efficiency&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kafka Brokers are stateless. It means that a broker doesn’t know which consumer has consumed till what offset. The consumer itself keeps track of the offset. It reduces overhead from the Broker. But there are cons as well. Deleting messages becomes difficult since the broker doesn’t know if all consumers have consumed that message. For this, Kafka gives a time-based SLA where retention policy can be configured for brokers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Brokers being stateless gives a side benefit to consumers to deliberately choose to rewind back to an old offset and re-consume(if the messages have not exceeded retention period, of course). Though, it is a violation of queue but has proved as an essential feature. For example, if consumer application feeding on data from Kafka has some bugs, then the data can be replayed after the bug has been resolved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Distributed Consensus&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s see how producers and consumers behave in a distributed setting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The producers produce data to a topic stored in Brokers and consumers consumer from these topics. Producers need to decide which partition to produce data. A partition can be randomly selected by the producer or by using a partitioning function.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consumers to a topic are put in a group called “Consumer Group”. Each message m of Topic T is delivered to only one consumer in the consumer group. At any time, all messages from one single partition are consumed by a single consumer. Different consumer groups independently consume messages from topics. No coordination is required among them. But within a consumer group, coordination is required.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The leader inside a consumer group is decided by a separate entity called &lt;a href=&quot;https://zookeeper.apache.org/&quot;&gt;Zookeeper&lt;/a&gt;. Kafka uses Zookeeper as a configuration store.
Zookeeper does these 3 things for Kafka.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Detecting the addition and removal of brokers and consumers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Triggering re-balance process in each consumer when the above event occurs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Maintaining track of consumed offset of each partition&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Re-balancing, whenever required, is taken care of by zookeeper by running a re-balancing algorithm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kafka uses Zookeeper to maintain 4 types of registries(config stores)for various purposes. Let’s quickly see what each registry stores.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Broker registry:&lt;/strong&gt; Stores information about brokers. It stores the host and port of the broker and the set of topics and partitions stored in the broker.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Consumer Registry:&lt;/strong&gt; Stores consumer group of each consumer and set of topics each consumer is subscribing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ownership Registry:&lt;/strong&gt; Stores one path for every subscribed partition and the id of the consumer currently consuming for this
partition. This consumer is said to own the partition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Offset Registry:&lt;/strong&gt; Stores for each partition, the offset of the last consumed message.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first three registries are &lt;strong&gt;ephemeral&lt;/strong&gt; i,e. if the creating client is gone, these path created in corresponding registries is removed from by zookeeper server. Offset registry is &lt;strong&gt;persistent&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each consumer has a watcher on both Consumer registry and Broker registry. Whenever broker set changes or consumer group changes or the startup of a consumer happens the watcher notifies consumers to initiate a re-balancing algorithm process. This is to determine new subsets of partitions it should subscribe from. To learn more about the re-balancing algorithm, read this manual.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Delivery Guarantee&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kafka only guarantees at least once delivery. By design, they didn’t want to go for the exactly-once guarantee, because that would have retired efforts in two-phase commits which were not necessary requirement for Kafka.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kafka also doesn’t guarantee to order of the messages. Since messages go to different partitions, can be consumed from different partitions as per the consumers want. So there is no inherent ordering of messages by design in Kafka. Consumers itself will have to take care of the ordering of the messages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kafka also takes care of the data corruption by giving Cyclic redundancy check at the message level. This allows you to check network error.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have been following up this far, thanks for reading. This blog is inspired by the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/research/wp-content/uploads/2017/09/Kafka.pdf&quot;&gt;Kafka white paper&lt;/a&gt;. I would suggest the readers explore &lt;a href=&quot;https://cwiki.apache.org/confluence/display/KAFKA/Kafka+papers+and+presentations&quot;&gt;this wiki&lt;/a&gt; to learn some more detailed concepts about Kafka.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Feel free to comment below your thoughts or connect with me on &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/whoAbhishekSah&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt; for any conversations on this blog.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[No Silver Bullets indeed!]]></title><description><![CDATA[This week I spent some time finding and reading about classical textbooks and papers in software engineering so far. This blog post is about…]]></description><link>http://abhisheksah.xyz/no-silver-buttes-indeed/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">http://abhisheksah.xyz/no-silver-buttes-indeed/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 08 Mar 2020 22:12:03 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;This week I spent some time finding and reading about classical textbooks and papers in software engineering so far. This blog post is about one of those highly esteemed papers written, titled &lt;a href=&quot;http://worrydream.com/refs/Brooks-NoSilverBullet.pdf&quot;&gt;“No Silver Bullet — Essence and Accident in Software Engineering”&lt;/a&gt; by Fredrick P. Brooks. This paper was written and published in 1986. Even after 34 years, this paper is widely discussed in the field of software engineering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
      class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-wrapper&quot;
      style=&quot;position: relative; display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;  max-width: 590px;&quot;
    &gt;
      &lt;a
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-link&quot;
    href=&quot;/static/84ab8a1e9b513d4f64d73c5d791fecce/a2510/1.jpg&quot;
    style=&quot;display: block&quot;
    target=&quot;_blank&quot;
    rel=&quot;noopener&quot;
  &gt;
    &lt;span
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-background-image&quot;
    style=&quot;padding-bottom: 135.8108108108108%; position: relative; bottom: 0; left: 0; background-image: url(&apos;data:image/jpeg;base64,/9j/2wBDABALDA4MChAODQ4SERATGCgaGBYWGDEjJR0oOjM9PDkzODdASFxOQERXRTc4UG1RV19iZ2hnPk1xeXBkeFxlZ2P/2wBDARESEhgVGC8aGi9jQjhCY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2P/wgARCAAbABQDASIAAhEBAxEB/8QAGAABAQEBAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAECAwT/xAAVAQEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAf/aAAwDAQACEAMQAAAB99RMOogMoP/EABkQAAIDAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABAhARIP/aAAgBAQABBQIwcR9uv//EABQRAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAACD/2gAIAQMBAT8BH//EABQRAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAACD/2gAIAQIBAT8BH//EABQQAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAADD/2gAIAQEABj8CT//EABoQAAIDAQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABECExEXH/2gAIAQEAAT8hvp4EtmoTHsq0JUf/2gAMAwEAAgADAAAAEB8wz//EABQRAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAACD/2gAIAQMBAT8QH//EABQRAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAACD/2gAIAQIBAT8QH//EABsQAQADAQEBAQAAAAAAAAAAAAEAESExQWGR/9oACAEBAAE/EEwoT7caFg37LEnkxxeey84fkJNSbvsap7+QhAUtogeCc5P/2Q==&apos;); background-size: cover; display: block;&quot;
  &gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;img
        class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-image&quot;
        alt=&quot;No Silver Bullets paper, image courtesy: Myself!&quot;
        title=&quot;No Silver Bullets paper, image courtesy: Myself!&quot;
        src=&quot;/static/84ab8a1e9b513d4f64d73c5d791fecce/1c72d/1.jpg&quot;
        srcset=&quot;/static/84ab8a1e9b513d4f64d73c5d791fecce/a80bd/1.jpg 148w,
/static/84ab8a1e9b513d4f64d73c5d791fecce/1c91a/1.jpg 295w,
/static/84ab8a1e9b513d4f64d73c5d791fecce/1c72d/1.jpg 590w,
/static/84ab8a1e9b513d4f64d73c5d791fecce/a8a14/1.jpg 885w,
/static/84ab8a1e9b513d4f64d73c5d791fecce/a2510/1.jpg 1000w&quot;
        sizes=&quot;(max-width: 590px) 100vw, 590px&quot;
        style=&quot;width:100%;height:100%;margin:0;vertical-align:middle;position:absolute;top:0;left:0;&quot;
        loading=&quot;lazy&quot;
      /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we have known that in the field of hardware(electronics) there has been a two-fold increase in the number of transistors that can be put on an IC every two years. This is referred to as &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Moore%27s_law&quot;&gt;Moore’s law&lt;/a&gt;. Fredrick argues that there is no single development technique which by itself promises even one order-of-magnitude improvement within a decade in productivity or in reliability or in simplicity in software engineering. There is neither any management technique as well which promises such improvements. There are no silver bullets in software engineering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But why is this case with software engineering? Fredrick analyses the intrinsic nature of the whole process that is “Software engineering” to find out why it is so. He finds two kinds of difficulties or complexities in software engineering. One is Essential difficulty and another is Accidental difficulty. Let’s go through each one by one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Essential difficulties&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fredrick goes on writing that the very nature of software is the root cause that there is no silver bullet. And this only makes it unlikely that there will be any silver bullet in future. We cannot expect any silver bullets in this field of ours. The essence of complexity in software engineering lies in data sets, relationships among those data sets, algorithms and invocation of functions. But the hard part of building software lies in specification, design and testing. There will always be syntax errors and need for improvement in the code, but they are tiny things compared to the bigger things like unclear specification, design flaws and loose testing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Software is perhaps much more complex than any other human construct because no two parts are alike. In this aspect, Software shows acute differences from hardware, automobiles or buildings etc. Scaling-up a Software entity is not merely a repetition of the same elements in a larger size rather it is an increase in the number of different elements. The elements, in most cases, interact with each other in some non-linear fashion, and the complexity of the whole Software increase in much more than linearly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From this complexity, comes the difficulty of communication among team members, leading to product flaws, cost overrun, schedule delays, the difficulty of enumerating, lesser understanding of all the possible states of the program and from that comes the unreliability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Changeability is one other kind of intrinsic difficulty with Software. All the successful software gets changed(evolved) as time passes. As software is found to be useful, people try it in new cases at the edge of, or beyond, the original domain. The vehicle on which software rides(the underlying hardware) is changing at a very fast pace. The software has to live beyond the life of the hardware.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Accidental difficulties&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are such difficulties which are not inherent to the domain but arise due to the interactions among the stakeholders and processes. There have been some developments in overcoming accidental difficulties in Software Engineering but these alone cannot promise order-of-magnitude improvements. Because they do not solve the inherent difficulties. Let’s go through some of the breakthroughs that solved accidental difficulties to some extent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;High-level languages are one such example. They have been the most powerful stroke for software productivity, simplicity, reliability and comprehensibility. High-level languages frees a program from much of its accidental complexity by providing abstractions over conceptual constructs. It eliminates a whole level of complexity that was never inherent in the program at all. But at some points, the high-level language becomes a burden, that increases the intellectual tasks of the user those esoteric constructs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unified programming environments like Unix have boosted productivity by integral factors. These integrated programming environments provide integrated libraries, unified file formats and piles and filters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Hopes for Silver bullets&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fredrick, next analyses, technical developments that are most often advanced as potential silver bullets. Ada and other programming languages solved some accidental difficulties by its philosophy of modularization and abstract data types. But surely, it will not prove as the silver bullet, as it another high-level programming language. Object-oriented programming looks like one more hope for a silver bullet to Fredrick. But object-oriented programming removes all the accidental difficulties from the expression of design. The complexity of the design itself is essential. And an attack on essential difficulties makes no change whatever in that. Similarly, Fredrick goes on discarding Artificial Intelligence, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Expert_system&quot;&gt;Expert Systems&lt;/a&gt;, Automatic programming, Graphical Programming, Program Verification, Environment &amp;#x26; Tools and workstations as silver bullets in Software Engineering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Attacks on Conceptual Essence&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fredrick goes on analysing some promising attacks on the essential complexity of Software. Buying software is one such approach instead of building it, as more and more vendors offer more and better software products for a variety of applications. They generally come with better documentation and somewhat better maintained than homegrown software. Better software has always shown remarkable improvement in productivity, for example, personal computers with well-generalized writing, drawing file and spreadsheet programs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Precisely deciding what to build is the hardest single part of building software. Most of the times client also doesn’t know what they want to bet built. So in planning any software activity, it is necessary to allow for an extensive iteration between the client and the designer as part of the system definition. It is really impossible for clients to specify completely, precisely and correctly the exact requirements of a modern software product before having built and tried some versions of the product they are specifying. &lt;a href=&quot;https://devsquad.com/blog/what-is-rapid-prototyping-and-why-is-it-used-in-development/&quot;&gt;Rapid prototyping&lt;/a&gt; has been a very promising attack on this essence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Software systems must be grown, not built. It should be grown in incremental development. The system should first be made to run, even though it does nothing useful except call some dummy subprograms. Then bit-by-bit it should be evolved into complex modules and function calls. Iterative development has shown dramatic results in projects. This also helps in building morale. Enthusiasm jumps when there is a running system, even a simple one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last piece of this analysis concerns with people. Fredrick argues, that we can get good designs by following good practices instead of poor ones. &lt;em&gt;Good design practices can be taught&lt;/em&gt;. Unix, Pascal, Smalltalk, Fortran are some examples of software that are the products of one or a few great designers. Fredrick advocates that the most important single effort we can mount is to develop ways to grow great designers. No software organisation can ignore this challenge. Good managers are scarce but no scarcer than good designers. Great designers and great managers are both rare. Organizations should spend equal effort in finding and developing great designers as they do on management prospects. For those are the people upon whom the technical excellence of the products will ultimately depend. Fredrick proposes few suggestions to grow great designers. Like systematically identifying top designers as early as possible. The best designers are often not the most experienced. Assign a career mentor to be responsible for the development of the prospect, device and maintain a career development plan for each prospect and provide opportunities for growing designers to interact with and stimulate each other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, for starters, this paper convinces me of not searching for any silver bullets. Moreover, it gives a better perspective to me at how to look at software, in terms of Essential and Accidental difficulties. This mind shift change actually lowers the burden of thought process in a day to day basis. I shouldn’t fight or worry about the essence of Software. It happens most of the times to us that we get exhausted or frustrated with the problems while developing software. Thinking those difficulties in terms of essential and accidental is a huge thought process change. Complex/hazy requirements, non-linear interactions of different pieces are all inherent to Software. I think this is both the beauty and the curse of this field.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Inspired from the paper, next I have picked the &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.codinghorror.com/recommended-reading-for-developers/&quot;&gt;Mythical Man-Month (anniversary edition)&lt;/a&gt;. A detailed blog on the book would follow later. Thanks for reading. Feel free to connect with me on &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/whoAbhishekSah&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt; for any conversations on this blog.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Books I read in 2019]]></title><description><![CDATA[I wanted to talk about the books I have read in 2019. I feel like I have learnt some good things from books and I feel like I should share…]]></description><link>http://abhisheksah.xyz/books-i-read-in-2019/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">http://abhisheksah.xyz/books-i-read-in-2019/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 14 Jan 2020 22:12:03 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;I wanted to talk about the books I have read in 2019. I feel like I have learnt some good things from books and I feel like I should share with everyone. So here we go!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It has been a good year since I started realizing the power of reading books. I spend most of my times with books related to the things I like viz: software development, astronomy, personal finances among many other things. A detailed list of books that I read in 2019 is here on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/user/year_in_books/2019/74087763&quot;&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;. This blog talks about the books I loved the most and recommend everyone to read once if interested in that genre.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will mostly talk about the books of Personal Finances and Astronomy. Let’s start with Personal Finances first.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Personal Finances&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Personal finances got my interest at the beginning of my senior year of college. I had taken a course called Financial Engineering and later on, I started liking the various concepts of finances(like options, trading, hedge fund market etc.). Later on, I read some books on personal finances. My personal favourite, on this topic, has been &lt;strong&gt;Rich Dad Poor Dad&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This book changed my vision of how I think about finances and expenses. This book teaches us the major difference between the Rich and Poor, which is the mindset (and money follows that). This book teaches you the mindset required to be rich. The author presents very good real-world examples which support his arguments. A simple example, taken from the book:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The poor and the middle class work for money. The rich have money work for them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book is filled with much such great advice which will change the way you look at your finances. Personally I agreed with almost all of the advice that was given in the book to be rich. But it is not an easy path to create wealth. The way we have been living our lives has conditioned us to the exact opposite(at least for me). So it requires a lot of discipline, and frequent self-introspection to ensure I am applying those learnings from this book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would highly recommend this book for anyone who has never cared about personal finances(literally, complete beginners) and who are struggling to get their financial situations right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was very keen to implement those learnings from Rich Dad Poor Dad, and so I started looking for books which teach what all financial instruments are available in India and their analysis. So the next book, I read was What Every Indian Should Know Before Investing. This is a great book for complete beginners who are not very familiar with the various financial instruments like Fixed Deposits(FD), Recurring Deposits(RD), Mutual Funds, Equities, and their tax implications. After gathering sufficient information, I started investing in multiple instruments. These books gave me enough exposure and confidence to take good care of my finances. Highly recommended!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Astronomy&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Astronomy intrigues me on a very different level. I like to read about the discoveries and happening of the outer worlds. This subject is just so delightful to read about on any given day. Cosmos by Carl Sagan is such a treat for astronomy lovers. In a 384 pages long journey with Carl, you will discover many worlds like Venus, Mars, Jupiter, Saturn. You will find out what these worlds are made of, the possibility of intelligent lives on these worlds and their probable fate. I love the way he presents information about these world by logical inferences which are so simple to understand, they don’t require a very sound understanding of the Physical Sciences. After reading the books by Carl, I would say he is the best teacher I have got in astronomy. His books always spark curiosity in me to explore the unknown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apart from these two subjects, I read a few books targeted on the contemporary political scenarios of India. The free Voice by Ravish Kumar is a good example which presents various incidents happened around India which reflect how India as a nation is changing democratically and culturally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, overall it has been a good year. I learnt a lot of new things and applied them in real life. Looking forward to an even great year ahead!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks for reading. Feel free to connect with me on Twitter for any conversations on this.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Object.assign() in JavaScript]]></title><description><![CDATA[Object.assign() is used to assign all enumerable properties of one or more source objects to some target object. Object.assign() is a very…]]></description><link>http://abhisheksah.xyz/Object.assign()-in-JavaScript/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">http://abhisheksah.xyz/Object.assign()-in-JavaScript/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2019 22:12:03 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Object.assign() is used to assign all enumerable properties of one or more source objects to some target object.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Object.assign() is a very useful and very frequently used method in JavaScript. It takes a target object and one or more source object. It modifies the target object with several usages listed below. Source objects are never modified.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Copying enumerable properties&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;javascript&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;language-javascript&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-javascript&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;var&lt;/span&gt; x &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt; a&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;5&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;var&lt;/span&gt; y &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;var&lt;/span&gt; z &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; Object&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;assign&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;y&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; x&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
console&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;log&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;z&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; y&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; x&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;//{ a: 5 } { a: 5 } { a: 5 }&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s see the usage of this method from some examples:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we can see, the variable &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;x&lt;/code&gt; has an enumerable property a which is equal to 5. By doing an &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;Object.assign(y, x)&lt;/code&gt; those enumerable properties of &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;x&lt;/code&gt; will be copied to &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;y&lt;/code&gt;. The copied object will be returned by this method.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Overwriting common enumerable properties&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Common properties of the target object will be overridden by values in source objects. Let’s see the usage of this method from some examples:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;javascript&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;language-javascript&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-javascript&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;var&lt;/span&gt; x &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt; a&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;5&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; b&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;7&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;var&lt;/span&gt; y &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt; a&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;4&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;var&lt;/span&gt; z &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; Object&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;assign&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;y&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; x&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
console&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;log&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;z&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; y&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; x&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;//{ a: 5, b: 7 } { a: 5, b: 7 } { a: 5, b: 7 }&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we can see, the variable &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;x&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;y&lt;/code&gt; have common property a. By doing an &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;Object.assign(y, x)&lt;/code&gt; the common enumerable properties of the target get overridden by that of the source.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Merging objects&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This method can also be used to create new objects by merging two or more variables. For example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;javascript&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;language-javascript&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-javascript&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;var&lt;/span&gt; x &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt; a&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;var&lt;/span&gt; y &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt; b&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;var&lt;/span&gt; z &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt; c&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;var&lt;/span&gt; v &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt; d&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;4&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;var&lt;/span&gt; w &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; Object&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;assign&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;x&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; y&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; z&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; v&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

console&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;log&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;w&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; x&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; y&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; z&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; v&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;// { a: 1, b: 2, c: 3, d: 4 } { a: 1, b: 2, c: 3, d: 4 } { b: 2 } { c: 3 } { d: 4 }&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although there is nothing different in the working on this method in this example, if you see it from the perspective of utility, you can use this method for merging multiple objects in one object. Here we are merging y, z, v, into a target object x.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;Object.assign()&lt;/code&gt; is very important method finding it’s usage at various places.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[The Problem of Pending Cases in Indian Courts]]></title><description><![CDATA[India is a vast country. It’s the second-largest in terms of population and the largest democracy in the world. But the Indian judiciary has…]]></description><link>http://abhisheksah.xyz/The Problem of Pending Cases in Indian Courts/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">http://abhisheksah.xyz/The Problem of Pending Cases in Indian Courts/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 15 Sep 2019 22:12:03 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;India is a vast country. It’s the second-largest in terms of population and the largest democracy in the world. But the Indian judiciary has not performed well in recent years. The judiciary (also known as the judicial system, judicature, judicial branch or court system) is the system of courts that interprets and applies the law in the name of the state. The judiciary can also be thought of as the mechanism for the resolution of disputes. Judiciary is the institution which protects the rights of citizens in a democracy. So it somewhat ensures social sustainability in a society(and hence nation).
There are more than 3 crore cases pending in the courts of India. The situation is worse than ever. The Chief Justices of India have constantly declared their concerns on this in recent years. It is one of the issues that need concerned authorities immediate attention. Otherwise, the nation will fail to build the very foundations of a sustainable society.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;An overview of the courts and court cases in India&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are three levels of courts in India. The district and session courts, the High Courts and the Supreme court of India. All of the courts have their proper roles assigned as per the constitution. The judges are there to resolve all the cases arriving in their courts. The cases can be categorized into three main categories:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Civil Cases: Civil cases involve conflicts between people or institutions such as businesses, typically over money. A civil case usually begins when one person or business (the “plaintiff”) claims to have been harmed by the actions of another person or business (the “defendant”) and asks the court for relief by filing a “complaint” and starting a court case.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Criminal Cases: A crime is always considered a crime against society, never against just the victim. So, there will be a police investigation. It will be the Prosecutor (The government) which will charge the accused and the victim shall not get to appoint a lawyer of his choice. It will be the government’s lawyer who will fight it. For example, the State of Maharashtra v/s Ajmal Kasab. The reason why ‘The State of Maharashtra’ comes into the picture is that crime is always considered as a crime against the entire society.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Writ Cases: A writ is a formal written order issued by a Court. Any warrant, orders, directions, and so on, issued by the Supreme Court or the High court are called writs. A writ petition can be filed in the High Court (Article 226) or the Supreme Court (Article 32) of India when any of your fundamental rights are violated.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;The present situation of pending cases&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As per the data collected from the National Judicial Data Grid, there are more than 3 crore cases pending in all the courts of India. Approximately 43 lakh cases are pending in the High Courts of India and 65,000 in the Supreme court of India. There are cases which are pending for years (even 10+ years). India is facing such a serious threat to social security. It is no less of a concern to every citizen. There is a saying that “justice delayed is justice denied”. The data clearly shows how many people have been, denied justice, due to the improper functioning of the judiciary. The below graph shows the pending cases in Indian courts. On the vertical axis is the count of cases and on the horizontal axis is the time for which the cases are pending.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
      class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-wrapper&quot;
      style=&quot;position: relative; display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;  max-width: 590px;&quot;
    &gt;
      &lt;a
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-link&quot;
    href=&quot;/static/5b29e9ba544485de1079ea6216ba5ba7/bba1f/1.jpg&quot;
    style=&quot;display: block&quot;
    target=&quot;_blank&quot;
    rel=&quot;noopener&quot;
  &gt;
    &lt;span
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-background-image&quot;
    style=&quot;padding-bottom: 91.8918918918919%; position: relative; bottom: 0; left: 0; background-image: url(&apos;data:image/jpeg;base64,/9j/2wBDABALDA4MChAODQ4SERATGCgaGBYWGDEjJR0oOjM9PDkzODdASFxOQERXRTc4UG1RV19iZ2hnPk1xeXBkeFxlZ2P/2wBDARESEhgVGC8aGi9jQjhCY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2P/wgARCAASABQDASIAAhEBAxEB/8QAGAABAAMBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAECAwX/xAAVAQEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAf/aAAwDAQACEAMQAAAB704aRcUqRYV//8QAGRAAAQUAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAQIQESAi/9oACAEBAAEFAnJ2FTX/xAAUEQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAg/9oACAEDAQE/AR//xAAUEQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAg/9oACAECAQE/AR//xAAUEAEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAw/9oACAEBAAY/Ah//xAAcEAABBAMBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABABARUUGhscH/2gAIAQEAAT8hnCgU2wPVyNApACm//9oADAMBAAIAAwAAABAvx4D/xAAVEQEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAARIP/aAAgBAwEBPxAj/8QAFREBAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAESD/2gAIAQIBAT8QY//EABwQAQEAAgMBAQAAAAAAAAAAAAERACEQcZFhof/aAAgBAQABPxCLRqH7gTQDwJFkF8WG9wpHaXhdqF6za08+YGf/2Q==&apos;); background-size: cover; display: block;&quot;
  &gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;img
        class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-image&quot;
        alt=&quot;Image&quot;
        title=&quot;Image&quot;
        src=&quot;/static/5b29e9ba544485de1079ea6216ba5ba7/1c72d/1.jpg&quot;
        srcset=&quot;/static/5b29e9ba544485de1079ea6216ba5ba7/a80bd/1.jpg 148w,
/static/5b29e9ba544485de1079ea6216ba5ba7/1c91a/1.jpg 295w,
/static/5b29e9ba544485de1079ea6216ba5ba7/1c72d/1.jpg 590w,
/static/5b29e9ba544485de1079ea6216ba5ba7/bba1f/1.jpg 840w&quot;
        sizes=&quot;(max-width: 590px) 100vw, 590px&quot;
        style=&quot;width:100%;height:100%;margin:0;vertical-align:middle;position:absolute;top:0;left:0;&quot;
        loading=&quot;lazy&quot;
      /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Out of the 3 Crore pending cases, 58% comes under the category of criminal cases and 42% under civil cases. Both types of cases have a different procedure of handling and so different problems are associated with them. If we look at the percentage-wise distribution on the age-group of pending cases, the data is rather shocking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
      class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-wrapper&quot;
      style=&quot;position: relative; display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;  max-width: 388px;&quot;
    &gt;
      &lt;a
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-link&quot;
    href=&quot;/static/e0a813e48f5f573828b9d222ca89a07c/c3c84/2.jpg&quot;
    style=&quot;display: block&quot;
    target=&quot;_blank&quot;
    rel=&quot;noopener&quot;
  &gt;
    &lt;span
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-background-image&quot;
    style=&quot;padding-bottom: 107.43243243243244%; position: relative; bottom: 0; left: 0; background-image: url(&apos;data:image/jpeg;base64,/9j/2wBDABALDA4MChAODQ4SERATGCgaGBYWGDEjJR0oOjM9PDkzODdASFxOQERXRTc4UG1RV19iZ2hnPk1xeXBkeFxlZ2P/2wBDARESEhgVGC8aGi9jQjhCY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2P/wgARCAAVABQDASIAAhEBAxEB/8QAGAABAAMBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAIEBQP/xAAWAQEBAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAACAQD/2gAMAwEAAhADEAAAAdmtKidsoFJcQqyFP//EABoQAAMBAAMAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABAgMRITP/2gAIAQEAAQUCtqVO6Z0avijLzqVSWMpn/8QAFxEBAQEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAQIQEf/aAAgBAwEBPwFl52cKTP/EABgRAAMBAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAECEBEh/9oACAECAQE/AVbuPCAZ/8QAGRAAAgMBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAEQICFR/9oACAEBAAY/AjVRGnY//8QAHBABAAMAAgMAAAAAAAAAAAAAAQARIVFhEHGx/9oACAEBAAE/IbXSvAyitB7gIz7G6aibkuX8StGaW/bx/9oADAMBAAIAAwAAABDfP/z/xAAYEQEAAwEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABABExEP/aAAgBAwEBPxBuitg2QCh5/8QAGREBAAIDAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAQARECFB/9oACAECAQE/ECHoOMSmopaY/8QAGhABAQEBAQEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAREAIVExQf/aAAgBAQABPxBpLVGVzfq4bMIUp+IsloUIuCkwWzzAO768vN00D4jExp4ugub5v//Z&apos;); background-size: cover; display: block;&quot;
  &gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;img
        class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-image&quot;
        alt=&quot;Image&quot;
        title=&quot;Image&quot;
        src=&quot;/static/e0a813e48f5f573828b9d222ca89a07c/c3c84/2.jpg&quot;
        srcset=&quot;/static/e0a813e48f5f573828b9d222ca89a07c/a80bd/2.jpg 148w,
/static/e0a813e48f5f573828b9d222ca89a07c/1c91a/2.jpg 295w,
/static/e0a813e48f5f573828b9d222ca89a07c/c3c84/2.jpg 388w&quot;
        sizes=&quot;(max-width: 388px) 100vw, 388px&quot;
        style=&quot;width:100%;height:100%;margin:0;vertical-align:middle;position:absolute;top:0;left:0;&quot;
        loading=&quot;lazy&quot;
      /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Considering the new cases to be those under 5 years of age, from the above figure, it can be seen that more than 60% of the pending cases are new. It also shows the awareness among the citizens of his/her fundamental rights. People are more aware than ever. The count shows that people are reaching the courts for justice in higher numbers. This puts a burden on the judiciary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Pending cases in different high courts&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The high courts are the principal civil courts of original jurisdiction in each state and union territory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
      class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-wrapper&quot;
      style=&quot;position: relative; display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;  max-width: 590px;&quot;
    &gt;
      &lt;a
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-link&quot;
    href=&quot;/static/9522cfbc8b88939b34e2a0b6dd9f2565/1a144/3.jpg&quot;
    style=&quot;display: block&quot;
    target=&quot;_blank&quot;
    rel=&quot;noopener&quot;
  &gt;
    &lt;span
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-background-image&quot;
    style=&quot;padding-bottom: 56.08108108108109%; position: relative; bottom: 0; left: 0; background-image: url(&apos;data:image/jpeg;base64,/9j/2wBDABALDA4MChAODQ4SERATGCgaGBYWGDEjJR0oOjM9PDkzODdASFxOQERXRTc4UG1RV19iZ2hnPk1xeXBkeFxlZ2P/2wBDARESEhgVGC8aGi9jQjhCY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2P/wgARCAALABQDASIAAhEBAxEB/8QAFgABAQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAQAF/8QAFQEBAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAH/2gAMAwEAAhADEAAAAd2RGZf/xAAUEAEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAg/9oACAEBAAEFAl//xAAUEQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAQ/9oACAEDAQE/AT//xAAUEQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAQ/9oACAECAQE/AT//xAAUEAEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAg/9oACAEBAAY/Al//xAAXEAEBAQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABABFR/9oACAEBAAE/IR7aFpIWG2F//9oADAMBAAIAAwAAABDfD//EABQRAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABD/2gAIAQMBAT8QP//EABQRAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABD/2gAIAQIBAT8QP//EABsQAQEBAAIDAAAAAAAAAAAAAAERACExQVFh/9oACAEBAAE/EDSLtZcrYFJ19xzchGc5VU3qaXg3/9k=&apos;); background-size: cover; display: block;&quot;
  &gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;img
        class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-image&quot;
        alt=&quot;Image&quot;
        title=&quot;Image&quot;
        src=&quot;/static/9522cfbc8b88939b34e2a0b6dd9f2565/1c72d/3.jpg&quot;
        srcset=&quot;/static/9522cfbc8b88939b34e2a0b6dd9f2565/a80bd/3.jpg 148w,
/static/9522cfbc8b88939b34e2a0b6dd9f2565/1c91a/3.jpg 295w,
/static/9522cfbc8b88939b34e2a0b6dd9f2565/1c72d/3.jpg 590w,
/static/9522cfbc8b88939b34e2a0b6dd9f2565/1a144/3.jpg 730w&quot;
        sizes=&quot;(max-width: 590px) 100vw, 590px&quot;
        style=&quot;width:100%;height:100%;margin:0;vertical-align:middle;position:absolute;top:0;left:0;&quot;
        loading=&quot;lazy&quot;
      /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Allahabad High court has the most number of pending cases. The shocking count of more than 7 lakh pending cases raise serious questions on the present and previous state governments of Uttar Pradesh. These figures somewhat show the ground reality of social sustainability in different states of India. Rajasthan being second and the High court of Punjab and Haryana also reflect the societal conditions. The below graph shows the percentage-wise distribution of pending cases in various states of India.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, there is a good side to this data. It can be seen that in the easternmost part of India, the states which are known as the seven sisters, are performing well when it comes to pending court cases but their population is also low compared to other states like Uttar Pradesh, Punjab, Haryana etc. A better insight would then be normalisation with respect to population of the states. See the chart below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
      class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-wrapper&quot;
      style=&quot;position: relative; display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;  max-width: 590px;&quot;
    &gt;
      &lt;a
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-link&quot;
    href=&quot;/static/f95a1fd183688a90254f71f30aaf4381/0c69d/4.png&quot;
    style=&quot;display: block&quot;
    target=&quot;_blank&quot;
    rel=&quot;noopener&quot;
  &gt;
    &lt;span
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-background-image&quot;
    style=&quot;padding-bottom: 67.56756756756756%; position: relative; bottom: 0; left: 0; background-image: url(&apos;data:image/png;base64,iVBORw0KGgoAAAANSUhEUgAAABQAAAAOCAIAAACgpqunAAAACXBIWXMAAAsSAAALEgHS3X78AAABd0lEQVQoz5VSiXKDIBT0/38xbRVQ4xlFCcilXcDMNJke0x1l4MG+c7MjYt937z02Q98XBWGUXq81UNU1Y4wURIg7br3fE7CXUmZd1zVto41JLrTeYBVCKKWkxKLuAdJamx48kfFOrMI59/XiWyjjxObgAfFP8i1gNM+OX+Cjx1naluuYvD/J+JFWOv+ElMyiXL+e1YVElMrGcRyGwTxq/iUyl7ZbniOD2fc9yHjwb3Lsqkzn/a+0u5e0b2MAJrFu1jkfWhlGfiLtsYIy300XGgZT6DkGmXHO53nGuZz1ZkN8F/I8wncccSiH0B6tVsbXqdvxFhlnoIK/LPz9g5RVTaAuxgrKqqpiZUUJpayktIyWMqeQXJ0T2o83Y3SWqlo5hyqrkhWEkKLgy9q1TZ6Ta101TQt9Xi5vlJDbNBV5jmgaSty27KU3UAxKjyLv2rZPFmQ4TROKxBGcU3BomH0A08IKl3FvxQoIdAvyhXHhHFpyEXjprIP9E67iK8lYILCLAAAAAElFTkSuQmCC&apos;); background-size: cover; display: block;&quot;
  &gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;img
        class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-image&quot;
        alt=&quot;Image&quot;
        title=&quot;Image&quot;
        src=&quot;/static/f95a1fd183688a90254f71f30aaf4381/fcda8/4.png&quot;
        srcset=&quot;/static/f95a1fd183688a90254f71f30aaf4381/12f09/4.png 148w,
/static/f95a1fd183688a90254f71f30aaf4381/e4a3f/4.png 295w,
/static/f95a1fd183688a90254f71f30aaf4381/fcda8/4.png 590w,
/static/f95a1fd183688a90254f71f30aaf4381/0c69d/4.png 598w&quot;
        sizes=&quot;(max-width: 590px) 100vw, 590px&quot;
        style=&quot;width:100%;height:100%;margin:0;vertical-align:middle;position:absolute;top:0;left:0;&quot;
        loading=&quot;lazy&quot;
      /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clearly, Sikkim has the worst condition. Per 100 person, there are 227 pending cases, while Kolkata stands second in this parameter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What actions have been taken in this regard&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can see that there is no one size fits all condition. India is a very diversified country culturally and economically. The problems faced by citizens in eastern India is very different than in the north. So the state and central government need to take different actions for different states. Proper feedback needs to be taken from the concerned authorities. A top-down approach will uproot the problem of pending cases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It also boils down to the problem of demand and supply. There is a demand for judges in all type of courts in India. But the recruitment process is almost dead. There have been several initiatives to recruit judges in an efficient manner. Several proposals were made like involving UPSC or another central agency may be in conducting the test, separately for district judges and subordinate court judges, in states and Union Territories, with due importance given to local languages for those opting for a particular state, on the lines of NEET held by the CBSE for medical students. It was also proposed for an all-India merit list to be prepared based on the proposed central selection mechanism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The initiative has got fresh impetus after CJI Ranjan Gogoi expressed his desire to fill up all judges’ posts immediately to bring down the huge pendency of cases in district and subordinate courts. At present, all appointments of judges in district and subordinate courts are in the domain of state governments and high courts concerned. Inordinate delays in holding a regular examination for recruitment of judicial officers for lower courts have led to huge vacancies. Though not all states and HCs are on board on the creation of the central mechanism, the CJI seems to have expressed willingness to go ahead with the as a one-time measure to fill up all vacancies and reduce pendency, sources said. The appointments will finally be made by the respective state governments based on the all-India merit list and HCs will have administrative control. The central selection mechanism is also intended to bring in uniformity in the appointment of judicial officers across the country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Reasons behind huge pending cases in Indian courts&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For what reason are such a large number of cases pending in Indian courts? Somewhere around 5 Cr cases are documented each year and arrangement of judges is of just 2 Cr. The reasons being:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Increase in the awareness of rights&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The number of cases being filed every year is increasing because of awareness towards justice increasing among people as literary rate increasing. The ongoing financial advances and the resultant consciousness of lawful rights, has offered boldness to ordinary citizens to approach official courtrooms for equity. For example, Kerala gets 28 new cases for every 1,000 individuals. It has an education rate of over 90%. Jharkhand, which has a proficiency rate of around 53%, gets four cases for each 1,000. It is a good thing, that people become more aware of their rights. Education provides them with the boldness to raise voice against things they find wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;New mechanisms like PIL and RTI&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the government explicitly made legislation for new rights like “Right to Information” and “Right to Education”, aggrieved parties started to increasingly knock the doors of justice. Likewise, a dynamic legal executive has imagined new gadgets like “Public Interest Litigation” which gave again brought about more cases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Inadequate judges&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are insufficient judges (just around 21,000). Current judge to population proportion is 10 to 1 million. The Law Commission report in 1987 prescribes at least 50 to 1 million. The population has expanded by more than 25 Cr since 1987. To remove the insufficiency of judges The Center Govt. says the States Govt. should take the lead in increasing the number of judges and the States Govt. says Center Govt. should take the lead. As this tug of war goes on, the judge’s strength continues as before and prosecutors stay in jail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More than half of the posts are vacant. There is a contention among Judiciary and Executive in regards to the appointment of Judges to Supreme Court and different High Courts. Colonial legacies like paid long vacations at a time when the number of judges is low, the appointed judges are taking long vacations, particularly in High Courts. These all lead to the reason for pending cases. The government needs to employ new judges to the courts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Inadequate courts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our judiciary has inadequate resources. Doesn’t have enough infrastructure, official buildings, etc. Both Central and States Government are not interested in increasing spending with respect to the judiciary. The Financial allocations for the whole judiciary are a pitiful 0.1% to 0.4% of the whole budgets. India needs more courts and more benches. Modernization and computerization have not reached all courts. The government need to come up with solutions to use technology for making courts more adequate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Low judicial quality in lower courts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of the cases are first heard in the lower courts and the number of cases which are referred to higher courts from lower courts for revisiting the cases is also high and one big reason for it is lack of trust of peoples on lower courts. In some cases, offenders appeal to higher courts just to delay his punishment. The quality of judges in lower courts is average and judicial is failed to pull the best talent into the legal executive. lower salary of officials in lower courts is also one of the reasons for it. Corruption is rooted in lower courts postponing dates and bribes for bail is also seen much time. To remarks these things former chief justice of India V. N. Khare said in an interview, “Judges are only human, like us. They come from the same society. Our society is all about quick successes. Short cuts are taken. Even by the judges.” Lack of experience and expertise of judicial officer in Lower courts to dispose of cases quickly is also one of the reason.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks for reading this review on Indian judiciary. Feel free to connect with me on &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/whoAbhishekSah&quot;&gt;twitter&lt;/a&gt; for any conversations on this or comment below.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Core value of core engineering]]></title><description><![CDATA[At Gojek, fresh graduates go through a rigorous two months Bootcamp programme. The Bootcamp is structured in several modules. The first of…]]></description><link>http://abhisheksah.xyz/core-values-of-core-engineering/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">http://abhisheksah.xyz/core-values-of-core-engineering/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 09 Sep 2019 22:12:03 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;At Gojek, fresh graduates go through a rigorous two months Bootcamp programme. The Bootcamp is structured in several modules. The first of these modules are core engineering. Here I will introduce you to some of the main themes of the core engineering module. Let’s dive in!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;How to make decisions, quickly!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An engineer is supposed to make many decisions every day. Decisions can be of many aspects ranging from how to name a variable to what should be the road map of the team for the upcoming days and months. This is a problem that we face several times a day. You can’t just take any decisions. You have to have some reasoning behind it. You must do some analysis of alternatives. Sometimes you have to convince your teammates about your approaches to a problem(what decision you took)! Here come the issues when you have to explain everyone and convince them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You need to develop many soft skills. No matter how smart you are or how great a programmer you are, but if you cannot communicate properly and if you cannot explain complex things to people in simple English, you are going to find it very hard to deal with people, every day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
      class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-wrapper&quot;
      style=&quot;position: relative; display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;  max-width: 590px;&quot;
    &gt;
      &lt;span
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-background-image&quot;
    style=&quot;padding-bottom: 75%; position: relative; bottom: 0; left: 0; background-image: url(&apos;data:image/jpeg;base64,/9j/2wBDABALDA4MChAODQ4SERATGCgaGBYWGDEjJR0oOjM9PDkzODdASFxOQERXRTc4UG1RV19iZ2hnPk1xeXBkeFxlZ2P/2wBDARESEhgVGC8aGi9jQjhCY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2P/wgARCAAPABQDASIAAhEBAxEB/8QAFwABAQEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAQCBf/EABYBAQEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAECA//aAAwDAQACEAMQAAABuxEG9zV5f//EABkQAAIDAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAECABEhIv/aAAgBAQABBQLQXycxibZmpbI//8QAGBEAAgMAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAEDERL/2gAIAQMBAT8B1Q5kf//EABYRAQEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAASE//aAAgBAgEBPwGWT//EABsQAAIBBQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAyEQESMVGh/9oACAEBAAY/AmkuqMNBsz0//8QAHRAAAgIBBQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAERITFRYXGBof/aAAgBAQABPyFQFRGgkkxJYNkui6mmFRj/AHSLynI//9oADAMBAAIAAwAAABAA/wD/xAAXEQEBAQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABABEx/9oACAEDAQE/EEdQXNv/xAAXEQEBAQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABABEx/9oACAECAQE/EBvISbf/xAAdEAEAAwACAwEAAAAAAAAAAAABABEhMWFRcaHB/9oACAEBAAE/EEzDJbC5WfZlQBJvLDJR3tEqtlZj3Zt9wQANurZ4MeYmtJWxPwn/2Q==&apos;); background-size: cover; display: block;&quot;
  &gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;img
        class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-image&quot;
        alt=&quot;IMAGE&quot;
        title=&quot;IMAGE&quot;
        src=&quot;/static/1c60f13e5be64a32b7b8b91e832e2d78/1c72d/1.jpg&quot;
        srcset=&quot;/static/1c60f13e5be64a32b7b8b91e832e2d78/a80bd/1.jpg 148w,
/static/1c60f13e5be64a32b7b8b91e832e2d78/1c91a/1.jpg 295w,
/static/1c60f13e5be64a32b7b8b91e832e2d78/1c72d/1.jpg 590w,
/static/1c60f13e5be64a32b7b8b91e832e2d78/a8a14/1.jpg 885w,
/static/1c60f13e5be64a32b7b8b91e832e2d78/dde82/1.jpg 910w&quot;
        sizes=&quot;(max-width: 590px) 100vw, 590px&quot;
        style=&quot;width:100%;height:100%;margin:0;vertical-align:middle;position:absolute;top:0;left:0;&quot;
        loading=&quot;lazy&quot;
      /&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;
Photo by &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/@austindistel?utm_source=medium&amp;#x26;utm_medium=referral&quot;&gt;Austin Distel&lt;/a&gt; on Unsplash&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Time is the most important factor&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Time is one of the most valuable resources for everyone in the office. So if you are making a conversation in your team, you need to be good enough to express your thoughts clearly and quickly. You need to learn how to speak clearly. In the Bootcamp, we go through a rigorous speaking drill where we practice how to be a good speaker and a good listener. Here I have learned how to convey your thoughts to your audience. An engineer has to deal with a wide range of audience working across different teams. For example, at Gojek, a product engineer may need to talk to Product Managers, Tech Leads, other engineers, business intelligence team, operations team, system engineers, peoples partner etc. There is a different level of engagement needed for different people. You need to put your words differently to be able to convey your message correctly and quickly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Be fallacy free&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of us fall in the trap of logical fallacies in our arguments. In the Bootcamp, we practice rigorously in speaking drill to make our arguments free from &lt;a href=&quot;https://owl.purdue.edu/owl/general_writing/academic_writing/logic_in_argumentative_writing/fallacies.html&quot;&gt;logical fallacies&lt;/a&gt;. We practice hard to inculcate the habit of making fallacy free arguments to sound convincing. Developing such speaking habits makes us reach an agreement in our arguments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, you will need your technical expertise in making decisions on a daily basis. But it’s not just about being technically sound, to be a great software engineer. It’s about those aspects of software development which are not taught in any university, the soft skills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Baby Steps&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The baby steps are about taking small steps to build the solution of a complex problem iteratively. Most of the time you don’t know prior to solving the problem what the solution is going to look like. In complex engineering areas, such as ours, most of the time we can’t say for sure for example how the service or app will look like in the end. There are many variables.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, the customer requirements are not clear initially or the scale is unknown or you are not sure about the approach etc. Baby steps help in these cases. In the core engineering Bootcamp, we develop the habit of taking baby steps in solving some problem because that way we will be able to solve some immediate problem which will, in turn, help you solve the bigger problem. This way you will do frequent commits. Baby steps should be visible on your commit history and not only on pen and paper. Test-driven development helps you take baby steps as you start seeing the bigger problem in smaller chunks of testable behaviours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Being a team player&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You are not going to work alone. You will always work in a team. We learn the principles of how to work in a team. In the Bootcamp, we also have a team of boot campers. We learn the process required to work effectively in a team. It introduces us to the most basic things in a team, for example, conventions, wiki, communication channel, stand up meetings, timings, objectives, limitations, approachability etc. What tools your team uses, what conventions you follow should be properly documented. The wiki should be the ultimate source of truth for every team member.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You won’t always write perfect code. No one writes perfect code. You will create technical debt and you cannot escape it. You take the decision that is best for the team and product. As an engineer, you have to decide what technical debts you can afford as a team. Some times you have to do the dirty work(e.g. not refactoring that code smell that you spotted) but you have to know how to repay as a team. By being a good team member is not only about being punctual or just doing your work. It is more than that. You should know what mistakes can you make and what mistakes you can afford. You need to be good at striking a balance between quality and delivering value.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of this can be cultivated when you have a belief in the processes that your team follows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Complex systems are such systems where output is not proportional to the input. Software is a complex system. The success of your product does not depend proportionally on the number of features you deliver. All of these above themes that I discussed above, help you chunk down the problem in smaller manageable batch sizes. In the hope that you deliver one feature correct and hopefully you will deliver the product right. These aspects help you make the correct software the correct way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks for reading. Feel free to connect with me on &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/whoAbhishekSah&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt; for any conversations on this.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[The evils of compulsory attendance criteria]]></title><description><![CDATA[Many engineering colleges in India have compulsory attendance criteria. For some colleges it is 60%, for some, it is 70%. During my…]]></description><link>http://abhisheksah.xyz/the-evils-of-compulsory-attendance-criteria/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">http://abhisheksah.xyz/the-evils-of-compulsory-attendance-criteria/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Aug 2019 22:12:03 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Many engineering colleges in India have compulsory attendance criteria. For some colleges it is 60%, for some, it is 70%. During my graduation, my college had compulsory attendance criteria of 85% and it still exists till date.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
      class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-wrapper&quot;
      style=&quot;position: relative; display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;  max-width: 590px;&quot;
    &gt;
      &lt;a
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-link&quot;
    href=&quot;/static/2f4cb1ae6fbe1eddbc788d10f37551f9/3c492/1.png&quot;
    style=&quot;display: block&quot;
    target=&quot;_blank&quot;
    rel=&quot;noopener&quot;
  &gt;
    &lt;span
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-background-image&quot;
    style=&quot;padding-bottom: 41.891891891891895%; position: relative; bottom: 0; left: 0; background-image: url(&apos;data:image/png;base64,iVBORw0KGgoAAAANSUhEUgAAABQAAAAICAIAAAB2/0i6AAAACXBIWXMAAAsSAAALEgHS3X78AAABAklEQVQY05VQXW+DMAzk//+vPW1DK2yt1u6BUOggXyTQJAQHMkNVaXuYtF0syzrlfCcnAJ7SA22PTdMIIYWUjPFhGKw1McZlQ7xj3oCM995am4zjyDhKOuecscY6e/sUwgxrBQgw4UMT76/GjG4MIdw2Jjhdqk/W8o6rTihBJaUMOwYQtEYSZyU0lpb9Ggx9NuCuZAK/r3f5Oc3K57xK38gLKU95mWbkMSMPyO+Kp/f29YMfTmKvjUJn5yzmxXQJzHCWhXC0B6lBXEFP4PqAs9RBbV0qL9SExcMC8RvW2M2lxV3x/1jFlLacMwwDMN355Zf6KUZBQSpS410MnvfvtnjwL45gy9PCT6eDAAAAAElFTkSuQmCC&apos;); background-size: cover; display: block;&quot;
  &gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;img
        class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-image&quot;
        alt=&quot;Scary email&quot;
        title=&quot;Scary email&quot;
        src=&quot;/static/2f4cb1ae6fbe1eddbc788d10f37551f9/fcda8/1.png&quot;
        srcset=&quot;/static/2f4cb1ae6fbe1eddbc788d10f37551f9/12f09/1.png 148w,
/static/2f4cb1ae6fbe1eddbc788d10f37551f9/e4a3f/1.png 295w,
/static/2f4cb1ae6fbe1eddbc788d10f37551f9/fcda8/1.png 590w,
/static/2f4cb1ae6fbe1eddbc788d10f37551f9/efc66/1.png 885w,
/static/2f4cb1ae6fbe1eddbc788d10f37551f9/c83ae/1.png 1180w,
/static/2f4cb1ae6fbe1eddbc788d10f37551f9/3c492/1.png 1300w&quot;
        sizes=&quot;(max-width: 590px) 100vw, 590px&quot;
        style=&quot;width:100%;height:100%;margin:0;vertical-align:middle;position:absolute;top:0;left:0;&quot;
        loading=&quot;lazy&quot;
      /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;
Source: My college email account&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Can you believe it? This much strict attendance criteria for the so-called elite engineering institution of India. My argument is that compulsory attendance criterion does more evil than good. It kills creativity and hampers the holistic growth of students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Teaching standards&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main agenda behind compulsory attendance criteria is to get students to class so that they can study the subjects taught in classrooms. There are several loopholes here. You need good faculty to teach subjects in such a manner that students take interests. Teachers should find ways and means by which studies can be made more interesting. A robust feedback loop needs to be in place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Compulsory attendance breeds incompetence as faculties are not worried about the number of students attending their class. They can teach in whatever manner they want to and get away with it. The mark of a good teacher is to attract students to the class and keeping them engaged for the entire duration of the lecture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What happens right now is, if the students don’t take interest in what is being taught, the administration forces them to attend the classes by threatening them with deregistrations from courses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Why is it bad&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using punishment to decrease behaviours(here not attending classes) is not working out very well for the wellness of students. Students do attend more classes but only because of fear. The actual passion for studying in class is lost. Anything which is forced upon someone will lose its charm. What is the use of un-interested students in a classroom? This is not education.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s pick an example of my college. IIT Jodhpur &lt;a href=&quot;http://iitj.ac.in/institute/index.php?id=vision_and_mission&quot;&gt;vision&lt;/a&gt; statement says that it “Prepares needed technical human resources to meet the technology challenges of the nation.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Can you see the irony here? To solve the technical challenges of the nation, one needs to cultivate a sense of creativity. Creativity refers to the use of imagination or original ideas to create something. To solve problems that were not solved before a person needs some sense of creativity. Creativity can not be forced. It can also not be taught in classes and labs merely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Students are bound with this huge attendance criteria and not set free. Creativity is something that comes independently and in full freedom. Creativity is killed if not given enough freedom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Better horizons&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a growing trend of freelancing, working part-time, on a project-by-project basis and working from home and this takes focus, dedication and time management — none of which is being inculcated in a higher-education system focused on rote learning and mere presence. Not everything is in classes and labs. Students need to be given the chance to make the best use of their time as per their discretion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most colleges in the Western part of the world do not have compulsory attendance, yet because of the quality of the classes, students attend them voluntarily. The classes are interactive. Students are given the freedom to choose their subjects and sometimes even given options in the method of evaluation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Strict attendance criteria force you to attend classes that you are not interested in. Colleges should focus attention on how much of the knowledge being imparted is willingly taken by students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks for reading. Feel free to connect with me on &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/whoAbhishekSah&quot;&gt;twitter&lt;/a&gt; for any conversations in this.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[India needs strict mob lynching laws]]></title><description><![CDATA[Mob Lynching in India Mob lynching mostly includes attacks by vigilantes, murder and attempts to murder, harassment, assault, gang-rape etc…]]></description><link>http://abhisheksah.xyz/india-needs-strict-mob-lynching-laws/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">http://abhisheksah.xyz/india-needs-strict-mob-lynching-laws/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Aug 2019 22:12:03 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;h3&gt;Mob Lynching in India&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mob lynching mostly includes attacks by vigilantes, murder and attempts to murder, harassment, assault, gang-rape etc. The victims are often brutally beaten, chained, stripped and hanged causing grievous injuries or death. One can include such attacks in the category of hate crime. In India, mob lynching has mostly happened because of cow meat-related incidents and Hindu-Muslim hate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As per NDTV India report, there was only 1 incident of mob lynching reported between 2009 to 2014 during the UPA government. But from the period of 2014 till present, 109 incidents of mob lynching were reported. 40 people were killed and 123 were seriously injured.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Why do we need strict laws for mob lynching&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is no present codified law against lynching in India as such, however, Section 223 of the Criminal Procedure Code contains the provision for persons being charged for an offence jointly when they are accused of the same offence committed in the course of the same transaction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just to highlight here, a trial court in Alwar acquitted all the accused on the benefit of the doubt in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ndtv.com/india-news/alwar-lynching-all-6-men-accused-of-beating-pehlu-khan-to-death-in-2017-acquitted-2085191&quot;&gt;Pahlu Khan lynching case&lt;/a&gt;. The video which recorded the crime was declared not solid evidence by the court. It was a failure of Rajasthan Police which resulted in justice denial for a victim.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given the situation of mob attacks in the country presently there is a need for separate legislation and strict implementation procedures to curb the attacks and punish the wrongdoers. The police and judiciary should resolve the cases of mob lynching very carefully. For this India needs strict mob lynching laws to establish a sense of fear in the wrongdoers.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Blockchain is revolutionary!]]></title><description><![CDATA[The problem with central ownership! In today’s era, data is everything. Whoever owns the data has the ultimate power. The central authority…]]></description><link>http://abhisheksah.xyz/blockchain-is-revolutionary!/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">http://abhisheksah.xyz/blockchain-is-revolutionary!/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 11 Aug 2019 22:12:03 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;h3&gt;The problem with central ownership!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In today’s era, data is everything. Whoever owns the data has the ultimate power. The central authority to data has started bringing us all kinds of evils such as data theft, data manipulation and unauthorised usage. The centralized world is failing us on data privacy and control.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The big giants(such as Facebook, Google, Amazon, etc.) are controlling the data and using that data to target us with ads and recommendations. We have seen what are the drastic implications of data misuse because of such central authority. The recent such incident with the application FaceApp. In this &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sydney.edu.au/news-opinion/news/2019/08/06/is-faceapp-hoarding-our-data-.html&quot;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt;, the University of Sydney describes how Faceapp could be misuse user’s data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;How Blockchain can solve this!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think blockchain can solve the problem of trust, security and ownership. At its heart, a blockchain is a record of transactions, like a traditional ledger. These transactions can be any movement of money, goods or secure data — a purchase at a supermarket, for example, or the assignment of a government ID number.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blockchain is designed to store information in a way that makes it virtually impossible to add, remove or change data without being detected by other users.
In the centralised internet, transactions are verified by a central authority. Blockchain applications could replace these centralized systems with decentralized ones, where verification comes from the consensus of multiple users. Blockchain usage algorithms based on cryptocurrency to solve these problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many countries have started using blockchain-based application which provides peer to peer trust, safety, security, no single point of failure and no centralized authority over customer’s data. &lt;a href=&quot;https://instadapp.io/&quot;&gt;InstaDApp&lt;/a&gt; is a good example of how DApps are gaining popularity.
Blockchain will be to businesses what the Internet was to communication. This is going to be the next big thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks for reading. Feel free to connect with me on &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/whoAbhishekSah&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt; for any conversations on this.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[REST vs HTTP]]></title><description><![CDATA[REST is a pretty common term that you will encounter now and then in web development. REST stands for Representational State Transfer. These…]]></description><link>http://abhisheksah.xyz/REST-vs-HTTP/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">http://abhisheksah.xyz/REST-vs-HTTP/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 11 Aug 2019 22:11:03 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;REST is a pretty common term that you will encounter now and then in web development. REST stands for Representational State Transfer. These are a set of core principles for architecting your software(mostly web services).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Initially introduced by Roy Fielding in his PhD dissertation, here I will try to explain in brief what those principles are, what it means to be RESTful, it’s different use cases and how HTTP comes into the picture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before getting into REST, we need to look at HTTP quickly. HTTP is an application layer data communication protocol on which(most of) the web works. This protocol defines how messages are formatted and transmitted and what actions web servers and browsers should take in response to various commands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;HTTP defines a set of methods to perform any action on a given resource. It has a pretty rich set of status codes which makes life way easier for a developer. There are various sophisticated features, also such as authentication, caching, cookies, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So you see REST is a way of architecting your application and HTTP is the protocol which defines how your application(web services) should be built. One can think of RESTful web services as such services which follow the REST guidelines. HTTP is merely an instantiation of the REST guidelines. Your application built on top of HTTP might be perfectly RESTful, partially REST or kind of 60% REST.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is very subjective how close is your software to being perfectly RESTful. Let’s see what should be the common characteristics in all RESTful applications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;URIs&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every resource(objects) must be uniquely identifiable by a URI. URI stands for Uniform Resource Identifier. Objects could be anything from multimedia objects(images, videos, gifs, etc.) to text files, database rows, etc. Anything that has merits to be identifiable gets a URI. There should be a single consistent naming of the resources. Here the developer should think what the right resources in your application are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Linking URIs&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These resources should contain links to other resources. Linking them is based on the fact that each has a unique ID. For example, you enter an address in your browser and get a web page(a resource) which links you to other resources. Representational resources link to each other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Uniform Interface&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;REST says you should have the same set of methods for all resources(uniform interface). HTTP makes this specific by its methods &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;GET&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;PUT&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;POST&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;DELETE&lt;/code&gt;, etc. So you see these methods define what action you could perform on the resources. REST defines these in a very general context. For example GET should be safe, idempotent and cacheable on all the resources. Similarly, there are semantics associated with other methods. It is possible that we could have more such methods, maybe in some other instantiation of REST. That point is REST doesn’t hold you back from having several methods on resources. But it should be consistent over the different type of resources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Interacting with the resources&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You interact with the resource through their representation only. For example if there is a customer resource identifiable by some URI. If you &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;GET&lt;/code&gt; it in &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;text/HTML&lt;/code&gt; format it should return you that format, or if you get it in &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;application/XML&lt;/code&gt; format, that should also work. RESTful web services allow you to interact with the same resource in different representations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Stateless communication&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The server does not store any state about the client session. Let’s see it by an example of a shopping cart on an e-commerce website. You can add items to your cart, and you can delete items from your cart. A shopping cart can be implemented in many ways. In one implementation, the server could send a link to your shopping cart. Because it is a resource and identifiable by a URI and also it can be linked to other resources. In another implementation, the shopping cart could be an unnamed client-specific state(session state). So REST says you should go with the first one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Why REST?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, you have other options also such as GraphQL. If you follow REST guidelines, then you can derive your application-specific interface from the REST specific interface. While doing this, the developer should take care of not violating the semantics associated with the HTTP methods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following REST lets you decouple your application also. Your client could be anything. It can be a browser, a terminal, another apache web server, proxy, etc. The client knows what result that its action is going to produce on the resources if the server is RESTful. For example, let’s say a client is searching for some resource on the server. If you have followed REST, then you have pretty robust GET on all the resources which return a readable representation of that resource. So that will let your client build fast and efficient search algorithms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks for reading. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.se-radio.net/2008/05/episode-98-stefan-tilkov-on-rest/&quot;&gt;SE-Radio Podcast with Stefan Tilkov&lt;/a&gt; inspires this blog. I tried to present the learnings in a brief, concise way. Feel free to connect with me on &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/whoAbhishekSah&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt; for any conversations on this.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Learnings in Gojek Bootcamp]]></title><description><![CDATA[This blog summarises what all things I have learned in the first week of GOJEK Bootcamp! Communication is hard! Until now, I was not even…]]></description><link>http://abhisheksah.xyz/Learnings-in-the-Bootcamp/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">http://abhisheksah.xyz/Learnings-in-the-Bootcamp/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 08 Aug 2019 22:12:03 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;This blog summarises what all things I have learned in the first week of GOJEK Bootcamp!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Communication is hard!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Until now, I was not even aware of this simple fact. In Bootcamp, we are learning how to speak clearly. The intent of the communication is that the person listening to you gets what you are trying to say. But different person perceives it differently. So it is your responsibility to make sure that you speak so rigidly yet simply that everyone in the room gets them exact same thing that you are trying to say. Speaking clearly and yet simplistically is hard. It comes with practice. You need to unlearn many things. You need to prepare your facts. You need to have a sound idea into your mind. Your arguments need to be logically consistent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Never love your code!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is also hard to do. But eventually, you will have to develop the habit of not loving your code. Because by doing so, you will lose the ability to evolve it. You will start taking the code reviews very personally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;A team has conventions!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have learnt how a professional team functions. It functions on the basis of a structure backed by conventions and automation. The team decides the convention they will use in their projects. The team decides the tools that they will use. They write the conventions in the wiki and treat it as the source of truth. We boot campers are also a team. We are learning how to pick our conventions. How to logically argue and reach a conclusion whenever there is a conflict amongst teammates. To do that, you need to learn how to speak clearly and resolving conflicts without wasting yours and others time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Any violation of conventions is not accepted. If code is violating any conventions it gets a &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;rm -rf&lt;/code&gt; harshly. This thing also serves as a positive learning reinforcement. And also contributes to the fact that you mustn’t love your code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To make sure you are not diverting from conventions, you use automation. Automation makes it easy to deal with rules in conventions. Otherwise, there will be inconsistency in the development process which will reflect in design, code and several other decisions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Simple English Modelling&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You should be able to express your intent in simple plain English. If you can do that, it will make it easier to make decisions quickly, argue rationally and will save everyone’s time. Most of the time we get diverted to other topics from the original topic in a discussion. Simple English modelling also help you not divert from the topic at hand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So that’s the learning of week one. Most of this was centred around processes and communication in a professional setting. It is making more and more sense, as we go deeper into the Bootcamp.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Peter Norvig is my role model!]]></title><description><![CDATA[Why do we need a role model? Everyone has desires. We want to achieve something to fulfil our desires. Most of the times, you can relate…]]></description><link>http://abhisheksah.xyz/peter-norvig-is-my-role-model!/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">http://abhisheksah.xyz/peter-norvig-is-my-role-model!/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 07 Aug 2019 22:12:03 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;h3&gt;Why do we need a role model?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everyone has desires. We want to achieve something to fulfil our desires. Most of the times, you can relate that by picking a role model. You want to orient your life around non-violence, Gandhi is probably the best role model. A role model is your benchmark. When you set a benchmark you tell yourself that this is the position I want to be, this is something I want to be. And you can measure how good or bad is it going for you for a certain period of your life, by the standards of your role model. You can evaluate your actions and their consequences on the longer objective of what you want to be like(i.e. your role model).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am a programmer. I want to be a good programmer, a better version of myself. I write software for a living. And I think this is not just another job. I find programming magical. Just look around yourself, in this era of automation, you will be able to appreciate the magic computer science has brought to us. I see myself writing good software solving real-world problems, which could add up to this magic in the years coming down the lane.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;My role model&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://norvig.com/bio.html&quot;&gt;Peter Norvig&lt;/a&gt;, an American computer scientist, is currently Director of Research at Google Inc. He is the co-author of &lt;a href=&quot;http://aima.cs.berkeley.edu/&quot;&gt;Artificial Intelligence: A Modern Approach&lt;/a&gt;, the leading textbook in the field of Artificial Intelligence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My first encounter with Peter Norvig was via this book only. I read this book as part of my graduation curriculum. This book gave me the vision of another form of magic that computer science brings to our life, the AI.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My next encounter with Peter was during a google search. A fine evening, I was doing a google search, on how to be a better programmer. I came across this &lt;a href=&quot;https://norvig.com/21-days.html&quot;&gt;blog post&lt;/a&gt; by Peter. This article gave me a different perspective, rather a life-changing. The arguments Peter made in this article really changed my views on programming and computer science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Peter has spent his whole life doing magical things in computer science, contributing to the larger context. I find Peter’s life to be very inspiring. Having worked in a huge set of domains in organizations like NASA, Google, Sun Microsystems, Peter continues to inspire me to be the better version of myself every day. He inspires me to learn, keep growing, moving fast, make some meaningful contribution to your field &amp;#x26; grow sustainably.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keeping the teachings of Peter Norvig in mind, I try to align my career decisions in the best way possible. And let me tell you a fact, it’s been working pretty good so far! There is a fair share of failures, but I find it very sustainable and fun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks for reading. Feel free to connect with me on &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/whoAbhishekSah&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt; for any conversations on this.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Refactoring by Martin Fowler]]></title><description><![CDATA[Refactoring is the process of changing a software system in such a way that it does not alter the external behavior of the code yet improves…]]></description><link>http://abhisheksah.xyz/refactoring-by-martin-fowler/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">http://abhisheksah.xyz/refactoring-by-martin-fowler/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 04 Aug 2019 22:15:03 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Refactoring is the process of changing a software system in such a way that it does not alter the external behavior of the code yet improves its internal structure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Why should you care about refactoring?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Design is a pretty sloppy heuristic. No design is final. You learn about your problem by actually solving it bit by bit. You improve the design as you get to know better about what you are trying to achieve. A poorly designed system is hard to change. Hard because it is hard to figure out where the changes are needed. If it is hard to figure out what to change, there is a strong chance that the programmer will make a mistake and introduce bugs. Refactoring will make sure your design is not decaying. It will make your program adaptable to upcoming changes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you find that yesterday’s decision doesn’t make sense today, you change the decision. Now you can do today’s work. Tomorrow, some of your understanding as of today will seem naive, so you’ll change that, too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You refactor as you make more sense of your decisions or when the decisions are no longer applicable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;A word of caution&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before we start refactoring, we should have solid tests. Solid tests only can give you 100% assurance that you didn’t break anything unknowingly while refactoring. While refactoring you must not add any features. You should not add any tests unless you find you missed one earlier. Doing refactoring you only restructure your code. Refactoring mostly changes the interface, so you might have to change tests in order to cope with a change in the interface of the code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you are adding a feature to your program don’t think about refactoring. Don’t think about changing existing code. You should only write your functionalities and get tests to work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Where can I refactor&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Any place where you see a code smell, it is telling you to refactor. The phrase Code Smell was popularised by Kent Beck. Code smells are characteristic in the source code of a program that possibly indicates a deeper problem(broken window?)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So you identify the smells and fix them by the best practices of Refactoring. The author has dedicated seven chapters on what sort of smells are and what refactoring technique is best suited to handle them with proper reasoning. We will have a quick overview of smells and refactoring techniques.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s Refactor!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Duplicated Code&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the most common form of smell. You can apply &lt;strong&gt;Extract Method&lt;/strong&gt; technique to make a separate method of the duplicated code. Here you take a clump of code and turns it into its own method. For example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;java&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;language-java&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-java&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;printOwing&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;double&lt;/span&gt; amount&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;printBanner&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;token class-name&quot;&gt;System&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;out&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;println &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&quot;name:&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; _name&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;token class-name&quot;&gt;System&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;out&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;println &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&quot;amount&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; amount&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;printBalance&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;double&lt;/span&gt; amount&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;printBanner&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;token class-name&quot;&gt;System&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;out&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;println &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&quot;name:&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; _name&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;token class-name&quot;&gt;System&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;out&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;println &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&quot;amount&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; _balance &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; amount&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Applying the extract method technique to this would give us&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;java&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;language-java&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-java&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;printOwing&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;double&lt;/span&gt; amount&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;printBanner&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;printDetails&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;amount&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;printBalance&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;double&lt;/span&gt; amount&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;printBanner&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;printDetails&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;_balance &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; amount&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;printDetails&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;double&lt;/span&gt; amount&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;token class-name&quot;&gt;System&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;out&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;println &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&quot;name:&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; _name&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;token class-name&quot;&gt;System&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;out&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;println &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&quot;amount&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; amount&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are many applications of the extract method technique. You can use it to make inline methods, replacing temporary variables with query methods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Long Methods&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A method is supposed to do one thing only. When you find a method that is doing more than one thing, it’s a smell. You need to decompose the method into several methods. You can use the above Extract Method technique or you can use Replace Temp With Query. Let’s see how Replace Temp with Query works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;java&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;language-java&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-java&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;double&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;calculateTotal&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;double&lt;/span&gt; basePrice &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; quantity &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; itemPrice&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;basePrice &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;1000&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; basePrice &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;0.95&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;else&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; basePrice &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;0.98&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Replacing the temporary variable &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;basePrice&lt;/code&gt; with its query method with yield.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;java&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;language-java&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-java&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;double&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;calculateTotal&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;basePrice&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;1000&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;basePrice&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;0.95&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;else&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;basePrice&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;0.98&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;double&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;basePrice&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; quantity &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; itemPrice&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Large Class&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When a class is trying to do too much, it often shows up as too many instance variables. When a class has too many instance variables, duplicated code cannot be far behind. We have seen how to deal with duplicated code. We can also split the class in two. Extract Class, Extract Subclass and Extract Interface are the refactoring techniques used when you encounter this type of smell.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Divergent change&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ever had a situation when a class has more than one reasons to change. This is a divergent change and a clear violation of SRP(Single Responsibility Principle). When you encounter this type of smell you need to split the class. The fundamental rule of thumb is to put things together that change together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Shotgun Change&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is opposite of divergent change. When you make a kind of change(let’s say you changed your database from Postgres to MySQL) and you have to make a lot of little changes to a lot of different classes, then you have encountered this type of smell. Use Move Method, Move Field, Inline class techniques to refactor such broken windows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Feature envy&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ever saw a method which calls so many methods from other classes. A method that seems more interested in a class other than the one it actually is in. Use Move Method, Extract Method, to place the method in the correct class.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Switch Statements&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Switch statements on class types are a smell. Most times you see a switch statement you should consider polymorphism. Use Replace Type Code with Subclasses, Replace Type Code with State/Strategy or Replace Conditional with Polymorphism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Middle Man&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Methods that are only delegating tasks to other classes can be referred to as the middle man. Use remove Middle Man, Inline Method or Replace Delegation with Inheritance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Data Class&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are classes that have fields, getting and setting methods for the fields, and nothing else. Such classes are dumb data holders and are almost certainly being manipulated in far too much. Data classes are like children. They are okay as a starting point, but to participate as a grownup object, they need to take some responsibility. Apply encapsulate field, encapsulate collection, remove setting method, move method, extract method.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a lot many refactoring examples in the book but I will conclude here. Thanks for reading. The book contains a lot more information on how to identify areas which need refactoring, how to refactor, what special care must be taken in particular techniques. Give it a read if you haven’t already.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Feel free to connect with me on &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/whoAbhishekSah&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt; for any conversations on this.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[TDD by Kent Beck]]></title><description><![CDATA[Test-driven development (TDD) is a way of managing fear during programming. To me, this is the best reason to use TDD. Fear makes you less…]]></description><link>http://abhisheksah.xyz/TDD-by-kent-beck/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">http://abhisheksah.xyz/TDD-by-kent-beck/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 04 Aug 2019 22:14:03 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Test-driven development (TDD) is a way of managing fear during programming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To me, this is the best reason to use TDD. Fear makes you less certain which will clearly affect what sort of code you are going to write(production or test).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fear makes you want to communicate less. What sort of effect would it have on your program when you have a constant fear and you can’t express your intent clearly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s get started with the introduction first!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TDD is a way of programming where you write tests first then you write the actual code. Let’s see this with an example.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You want to write a method which adds two numbers and returns the output. How will you write a code for this function?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trick question. In TDD, you don’t think of code. You think of tests first. What set of tests when passed will demonstrate the presence of code we are confident will perform addition of two numbers. Once you have decided those test cases. You write the tests and run them. Obviously, they will fail(might not even compile) because the code is not there. Then you add the minimum amount of code required to make the tests pass. Once you do that you remove the duplication that you have introduced this way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A TDD way of writing software looks kind of like this-&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add a little test&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Run all tests and fail&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make a little change&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Run the tests and succeed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Refactor to remove duplication&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is referred to as the Red-Green-Refactor cycle, the mantra of TDD!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To make the tests pass, you might have introduced duplication. Duplication is a symptom of a problem called dependency. Duplication most often takes the form of duplicate logic — the same conditional expression appearing in multiple places in the code. Objects are excellent for abstracting away the duplication of logic. By eliminating duplication before we go on to the next test, we maximize our chance of being able to get the next test running with one and only one change. We must get rid of the duplication between the test code and the working code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you are at RED, you quickly want to get to GREEN. How can you do that? Kent Beck tells 3 ways of getting to green quickly. The first two are fairly simple.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fake It — return a constant from code and gradually replace constants with variables until you have the real code.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Obvious Implementation — type in real implementation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When everything is going smoothly and you know what to type(Like the addition of two numbers), you put in obvious implementation after obvious implementation (running the tests all the time to ensure that what’s obvious to you is still obvious to the computer).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As soon as you to get an unexpected red bar(not everything is as obvious as an addition), you back up, shift to faking implementations and refactor to the right code. When your confidence is back, you go back to obvious implementations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The third way of getting to green quickly is triangulation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Triangulation — You Change certain important knowledge in the system and assert that the production code behaves in an accordingly expected manner. Use triangulation when you can’t see a way of eliminating duplication between code and tests. When you cannot think of what axes of variability are you trying to support in your design, make some of them vary and the answer may become clearer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Doing clean code, you get the benefit of complete code coverage. You are confident about your design decisions. You move quickly. You don’t fear changes because you have tests that will tell you what you need to do next. You get the flexibility of easily refactoring your system because you have solid tests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By practice, you learn to take small steps when you don’t know what is your code going to be. You take large steps when you know what your implementations are going to be. The size of your steps is dependent on the scope of the test.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TDD is very easy in many languages and testing framework such as Ruby with RSpec, even JAVA. With some langauges, TDD is tedious because of the whole Red-Green-Refactor cycle being large to handle in continuation. Experimentation also becomes tedious in such cases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So that was a brief moment of ours with the book TDD by Kent Beck. Thanks for reading !!!
Feel free to connect with me on &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/whoAbhishekSah&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt; for any conversations on this.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Clean code]]></title><description><![CDATA[Writing clean code is what you must do in order to call yourself a professional. There is no reasonable excuse for doing anything less than…]]></description><link>http://abhisheksah.xyz/clean-code/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">http://abhisheksah.xyz/clean-code/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 04 Aug 2019 22:13:03 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Writing clean code is what you must do in order to call yourself a professional. There is no reasonable excuse for doing anything less than your best!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best measurement of code quality is WTFs/minute!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So let’s get straight into actionable insights on how to reduce the above metric!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Meaningful Names&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Naming is hard! Few things to take care while naming your variables and methods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use intention revealing names&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Avoid disinformation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make meaningful distinctions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use pronounceable names&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use searchable names&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Follow common conventions of the programming language you are using&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Class names should be noun phrases&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Method names should be verb phrases ​&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Functions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Functions should be small. 4–5 lines is a very good metric. But it is very much specific to your choice of programming language. But the lesser, the better.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Functions should do one thing only.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There should be only one level of abstraction per function. For example, avoid doing tasks such as inserting employee object to a list and generating the employee payslip in a single function. Because those are a different level of abstractions. Also violates the doing one thing principle.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Avoid switch statements. Switch statements imply your function is doing more than one thing based on some condition. Think of a better way to express your thoughts(Polymorphism maybe?)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use descriptive names&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An optimal number of arguments to a function is zero. In the worst case, you can have one or two arguments. But more than two is a strict red alert. If a function has more than two arguments if possible make them a new class (if possible)!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Never use flag arguments. Flag arguments mean your function is doing two things. You need to split your function.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don’t have side effects associated with calling your function. No hidden-changes. Clearly, do one thing!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Return value objects. Value objects are objects whose instance variables never change once they have been set in the constructor. Value objects biggest advantage is that they save you the trouble of nonorthogonality.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prefer exception to return error codes. Use try-catch in place of if-else!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;DRY — Don’t Repeat Yourself! Eliminate duplication at all cost.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Comments​&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Best comments are no comments — Comment show your inability to write clean code that expresses your intent.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Formatting&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Indentation ​is most important.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There shouldn’t be any blank lines in between function. A blank line should mark a logical separation in methods, classes etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Instance variables should be placed at the starting of the class on top of methods.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The caller should be above the callee. (But language-specific!)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Focus on readability by giving appropriate vertical density.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Objects and Data Structure​&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is the difference between Objects and Data Structure?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Objects hide their data behind abstractions and expose functions that operate on that data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Objects do not expose data. Rather express their data in abstract terms.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Data Structures expose their data and have no meaningful functions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes we need to use data structure, sometimes we need to objects and sometimes both. So we should be able to tell&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With objects, we need to follow the Law of Demeter. Law of Demeter says that a method &lt;em&gt;f&lt;/em&gt; of Class &lt;em&gt;C&lt;/em&gt; should only call methods of&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;C&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An object created by &lt;em&gt;f&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An object passed as an argument&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An object held as an instance variable of &lt;em&gt;C&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Failing law of Demeter implies a function knows many things. Split that function into multiple functions. It could be split into several one line functions that delegate the task to other methods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Error Handling&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use exceptions rather than error codes ​&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Unit Test&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TDD is encouraged to be followed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tests must be clean (Readability). Don’t treat tests as second class citizens. Your tests should also be written following all the clean code conventions. Test code is as important as production code.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Test coverage should be always high.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Try to have only one assertion per test. If not then try to minimize the number of assertions per test. There should be a single concept per test.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Follow the F.I.R.S.T acronym with unit tests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;F — Tests should run fast&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I — Tests shouldn’t depend on each other&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;R — Tests should be repeatable in any environment&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;S — Tests should be self-validating (Test should have a boolean output)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;T — Tests should be written Timely ​&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Classes​&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Never have a public variable —this implies bad encapsulation. You should protect your classes privacy from the outer world.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Classes should be small. It should be smaller than that.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One class should have an only responsibility — SRP: Single Responsibility Principle. SRP means a class should have only one reason to change.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Class Name should describe what responsibility it fulfils.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A class should have high Cohesion. Maximum cohesion is achieved when each instance variable is used by each method.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When classes lose cohesion split them. It means SRP is being violated. Abstractions are getting mixed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Emergence​&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Systems that are not testable are not verifiable if not verifiable then not deployable. RUN ALL THE TESTS&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Refactoring is something which will help your system emerge. When refactoring you should remove duplication. When you refactor try to be more expressive with your intent. Impose SRP on your modules. Refactor them if SRP is being violated. ​&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Few more tips!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Building your project(compilation, testing, packaging) should be easy. One should be able to build via a single command or a few commands only. It should bot involve various different checkpoints.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All test should run with one command.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Avoid multiple languages in one source file. ​&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Avoid Surprises ​&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Never overwrite Safety. This means to take care of your warnings. Simply suppressing your warnings could result in Chernobyl! A disaster.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Eliminate duplication. Follow DRY: Don’t Repeat yourself&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don’t Mix levels of Abstraction. Follow the law of Demeter.​&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Always remove dead code.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Always maintain consistency ​throughout your project.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Be as expressive as possible.​&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don’t mix responsibilities.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make logical dependencies physical.
​&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prefer Polymorphism to if-else, switch cases ​&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Encapsulate conditionals, boundary conditions, edges cases&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So that was a brief summary of writing clean code.
Thanks for reading. Feel free to connect with me on &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/whoAbhishekSah&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt; for any conversations on this.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Pragmatic Programmer]]></title><description><![CDATA[A great book for anyone who wants to become a more effective and productive programmer! This book contains great tips on how to be one! What…]]></description><link>http://abhisheksah.xyz/pragmatic-programmer/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">http://abhisheksah.xyz/pragmatic-programmer/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 04 Aug 2019 22:12:03 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;A great book for anyone who wants to become a more effective and productive programmer! This book contains great tips on how to be one!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What is pragmatic, you may ask&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being pragmatic is all about being skilled in business, caring about your craft. Skill and craft come from experience. It comes from facing failures, learning things and not being afraid of them. Take this to the field of programming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What makes a pragmatic programmer?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pragmatic programmers are fast adopters. They are always inquisitive — asking lots and lots of questions. They are critical thinkers. They don’t operate on auto-pilot. They are the jack of all trades.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They take responsibilities. They don’t make lame excuses. When they make a mistake they accept it and provide options. They don’t play the blame game. They don’t live with broken windows(a bad design decision, poor code etc.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They invest in their knowledge portfolio every day. They keep on diversifying the knowledge portfolio.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;A Pragmatic approach&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are some ideas which apply to almost every type of software development. A set of ideas and processes which help you build better software.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Duplication&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Duplication is the root cause of all evil. Duplicated logic is hard to deal with. It’s hard to refactor. It is a broken window. We fix all the broken windows. There could be various causes of duplication arising. It could be because of multiple representations of information, comments, language issues. It could have arisen from mistakes in design. Taking shortcuts because of lack of time mostly results in duplications. Remove duplications at all costs. Follow DRY: Don’t Repeat Yourself!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Orthogonality&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two or more things are orthogonal if a change in one doesn’t affect the other. We want to design components that are self-contained, independent and with a single well-defined purpose. You get a lot of benefits from orthogonality. By promoting orthogonality, you are promoting reusability, which in turn makes you productive. Orthogonality applies to code, to design and even teams. We should maximize orthogonality. Make your module easy to reuse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Reversibility&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One thing you should always keep in mind is that there are no final decisions. Make your software architecture flexible. Make it easy to accommodate changes. In an object-oriented way of programming, you can achieve this with low coupling, good encapsulation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Tracer Bullets&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use tracer bullets to find you want to achieve. The tracer bullet method involves implementing a new application end-to-end to test every layer or component’s interaction. They are preferred to the labour of calculation. Using tracer bullets users get to something working very quickly. Developers build a structure to work in. You have an integration platform. You have something to demonstrate. You have a better feel for progress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Prototype&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anything that you are not comfortable with could be prototyped. You can prototype architecture, new functionality, third party tools or UI design. Prototyping could be done in several ways. Prototyping is a learning experience. You build some disposable product, maybe using a totally different technology stack from the original product. You learn what you want to build using prototypes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Basic Tools&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every craftsman needs a good set of tool to be productive and carry out the job effectively. For a programmer, these are some of the basic tools that you need to get comfortable with :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Up your shell game. Shell commands make you highly productive. Compare that to the GUI way of doing it and you will find out. Learn the shell commands and use them. The more you use them, the better you get at it. I have found stream editor(sed) magical. Exploiting the benefits of pipelines, redirection &amp;#x26; composability, you can bring wonders through one single command.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use a single editor well. Learn all the shortcuts and keymaps that you need to apply every moment. Vim vs VSCode should not be an argument. Whatever gets your job done and makes you productive, go for it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Always use source code control. Git is the best(my opinion 😝 )!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Develop debugging psychology. Don’t panic when an error popups. While debugging, don’t assume something, rather prove it. This will save you from the trouble of blaming the system for a fault that is likely to be your own (select isn’t broken!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Pragmatic Paranoia&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Accept the fact that you can’t write perfect software. Because it doesn’t exist. No one writes perfect software. You should be convinced of the fact that you also don’t write perfect software. Pragmatic Programmers code in defences against their own mistakes. Here are some defensive measures that you can take.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Design by Contract&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bertrand Meyer came up with this elegant concept. Before a function starts, it may have some expectation of the state of the world, and it may be able to make a statement about the state of the world when it concludes. Its a contract between a function and any potential caller:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If all the routine’s preconditions are met by the caller, the routine shall guarantee that all postconditions and invariants will be true when it completes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you design by contract you be strict in what you will accept before you begin and promise as little as possible in return.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Crash Early&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you follow DBC(Design by Contract), it’s much easier to find and diagnose the problem by crashing early, at the site of the problem. You can easily found out where was the breach of contract. This way you will avoid any surprising results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Assertive Programming&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea is that “if it can’t happen, use assertions to ensure that it won’t.” Assertions check for things that should not happen. Assertions will save the day when you hit an error as silly as array being null, the string being empty, array not sorted etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Exception Handling&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use exceptions but don’t abuse your program in a messy unexceptional way. Use exceptions for exceptional problems. Something being exceptional depends on the context. A FileNotFound could qualify as an exception when you are expecting it should have been there. But when you are not sure whether the file should be there, raising an error seems an appropriate response.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Resource Handling&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many of the time we forget to close the file we opened to write. This could hit us in pretty serious problems when scaled. Always have a consistent plan to deal with resource allocation and deallocation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Bend or Break&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your program should be flexible and adaptable in the face of an uncertain world. How can you achieve that?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Law of Demeter&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Uncle Bob martin describes the law of Demeter as below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A method &lt;em&gt;f&lt;/em&gt; of Class &lt;em&gt;C&lt;/em&gt; should only call methods of&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;C&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An object created by &lt;em&gt;f&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An object passed as an argument&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An object held as an instance variable of &lt;em&gt;C&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What happens when you don’t follow the law of Demeter?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You end up having lots of coupled classes. This will restrict your flexibility. Orthogonality will be compromised. So follow the law of Demeter. Organise your code into modules and limit the interaction between them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Metaprogramming&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The systems that we are trying to build should be highly configurable. Use metadata to describe configuration options for an application. Switching communication port should be better done via configuration than getting into the coding details. We should appreciate the values of metaprogramming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Temporal coupling&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are various things in our day to day life which can be made concurrent. So are in software. Many of the tasks don’t depend on each other, so executing them concurrently can give a great deal of performance improvement. Temporal coupling is about analyzing workflow to find and improve concurrency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;While you are coding&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some advice on how you should code and how you should not!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Program by Coincidence&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ever faced the situation when you don’t know why the code is failing because you didn’t know why it worked in the first place. It seemed to work, given the limited “testing” that you did, but that was just a coincidence. I had many of these moments. So code deliberately. Proceed with a plan, always be aware of what you are doing and document your assumptions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Estimating algorithm speed&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Estimate the runtime of your algorithm. A Big-O analysis of your codebase would help you identify major areas of improvement in terms of computation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Refactoring&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Refactoring is a change made to the internal structure of software to make it easier to understand and cheaper to modify without changing its observable behaviour. We refactor to make sure our program is not rotting. You should refactor when you see a violation of the DRY principle. When you see nonorthogonality try to refactor to the best possible extent. Remove outdated knowledge from the codebase. Refactor early, refactor often.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Testing&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lot has been said and discussed on testing. You should write proper unit tests. Testing is more cultural than technical. It’s language and framework independent. Create a culture of testing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Before the project&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of the times when a project starts, requirements are not locked. Requirements are never fixed. They keep evolving as the customer and the developer get closer to understanding what they want to consume/build. Most of the times we need to dig for requirements by having one on one sessions with the consumer to identify the expectations rigidly.
Promote abstractions. Talk in terms of abstractions because abstractions live longer than the implementations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So that was a brief summary of what makes a pragmatic programmer. I have started to adopt these pieces of advice as I care more of my craft now than ever.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks for reading !!! Feel free to connect with me on &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/whoAbhishekSah&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt; for any conversations on this.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Freya - The fondness for lambda architecture]]></title><description><![CDATA[How we went on building a product which can handle a huge amount of incoming data and process it online. Hi Everyone, I am here to talk…]]></description><link>http://abhisheksah.xyz/Freya - the-fondness-for-lambda-architecture/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">http://abhisheksah.xyz/Freya - the-fondness-for-lambda-architecture/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 30 Mar 2019 22:12:03 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;How we went on building a product which can handle a huge amount of incoming data and process it online.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hi Everyone,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am here to talk about one of the projects that I did at my college. I took up this project during the final year of engineering at IIT J. This project is actually very different compared to other projects that I had done until then(which includes web development, NLP, Machine Learning etc.). We were a team of two. We had our fair share of difficulties and hurdles on the way. But that’s where the learnings come from 😃.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Problem Statement:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Handling inflow of huge amount of data and processing it online.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s try to visualise the problem statement with a use case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consider an academic institution such as mine. When some student wants to perform data processing for her project on some huge amount of data, it is very tough to do it on her single computer/laptop due to the resource limit. We are talking data of terabytes and petabytes scale. So doing the processing on a single computer will take forever. We want to develop a solution for this pro­blem. The commodity PCs at the computer laboratory can be used to distribute the task in hand. We want to develop a system so generic which will perform the desired job on the huge incoming data by processing it online. We also want it to be fault tolerant at all times. There are plenty of tools that do distribute computing but rarely there are such systems for this context.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So let’s say we have an incoming stream of images and the developer wants to run some classification algorithm over those images. The result of this classification should be written in a database for online queries. Running the desired job on each piece of data(here classification of images) linearly will take forever.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Can we distribute the classification task to more computers and aggregate the result when the job is done?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://lambda-architecture.net/&quot;&gt;Lambda Architecture(LA)&lt;/a&gt; is one such solution. Nathan Marz described lambda architecture as a robust, scalable, generic, distributed system. Let’s talk about how LA handles this. Please bear with me. It will be worth it 😇.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What is Lambda Architecture&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It all begins with data. Data of any type e.g. logs from a mobile application, location pings, images, audio, videos, banking transaction. The raw data is stored in the data centres. On top of that various operations are performed. LA makes two assumptions on the data. The assumption on this data is that it is online and it is immutable. The former online, here means that we are appending the new data at the end of existing data. The latter term immutable, means we are not changing any data at any point in time. Updates are replaced by new writes. I’ll justify these assumptions in a while.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now you have queries on the data (the whole dataset). Literally running a function on the complete dataset has latency constraints as dataset size grows. For the time being let’s assume we are able to compute our function quickly on complete dataset. Talking about CAP theorem, partition tolerance is a necessity and not an option. So the tradeoff is between consistency and availability. Nathan Marz, proves in his work, that how mutable data and CAP theorem don’t play well together (the complexity of read-repairs). However, if we remove the updates by new writes there won’t be any divergent values at any point in time. So we will be able to achieve eventual consistency along with availability. CAP theorem has been beaten.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Talking about eventual consistency, we assumed that our function runs quickly on the entire dataset. This can be achieved by using a data system which can easily store large and constantly growing dataset and can compute the function in a scalable way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To get results quicker, we can precompute the batch views and store in a database. This database can be indexed on the timestamp for quicker queries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only drawback that can arise here as the data grows is that the queries are out of date by a few hours. There will be eventual consistency. All that is left to do is to compensate for the last few hours of data. Nathan proposes a real-time system that computes the query on the last few hours of data for which batch view has not been calculated. This can be done quickly. So to finally answer a query on the whole dataset, we can merge the results from batch view and real-time view. The last few hours of data are again sent to batch layer for batch view precomputation. Let’s understand this approach with an example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s say you have 100 GB of images so far and the data is ever increasing. You compute you classification job on this whole dataset in let’s say ~5 hrs. You have written the result of this computation in a dataset indexed with the timestamp. Now say 10 MB of new images have arrived. Recomputing the classification job on 100GB+10MB will again take ~5 hrs. This will be really an inefficient way of handling the data and queries since you’ve precomputed the result on 100GB earlier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;How does Lambda Architecture work?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can process the existing data in a batch processing framework(e.g Apache Hadoop), writing the result of the classification job in a database. So we have precomputed the batch view. The new incoming data can be processed inside a real-time processing framework(e.g. Apache Storm) and the result could again be written in a separate database. When a user queries about the job on the whole dataset, we can show results of the precomputed batch views aggregated with real-time views quickly. The new data can be sent again to the batch layer to be appended and job to be recomputed in the background on the new batch view. That way we have distributed the job among many computers and answering queries quickly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Building Blocks of Freya&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Freya extends this same idea in our context. You give it some computers with Ubuntu installed on them connected in a network. It will set up the batch layer and real-time layer along with a database gateway to query on the data. We used Apache Hadoop for the batch layer and Apache Storm for the real-time layer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The batch layer of Freya is a master-slave Hadoop architecture. Master node runs the NameNode and the slave nodes act as DataNodes. Here is a diagram describing this architecture:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
      class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-wrapper&quot;
      style=&quot;position: relative; display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;  max-width: 590px;&quot;
    &gt;
      &lt;a
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-link&quot;
    href=&quot;/static/31c8e6d965c11e632ba9b164be204fd8/c84e8/1.jpg&quot;
    style=&quot;display: block&quot;
    target=&quot;_blank&quot;
    rel=&quot;noopener&quot;
  &gt;
    &lt;span
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-background-image&quot;
    style=&quot;padding-bottom: 53.37837837837838%; position: relative; bottom: 0; left: 0; background-image: url(&apos;data:image/jpeg;base64,/9j/2wBDABALDA4MChAODQ4SERATGCgaGBYWGDEjJR0oOjM9PDkzODdASFxOQERXRTc4UG1RV19iZ2hnPk1xeXBkeFxlZ2P/2wBDARESEhgVGC8aGi9jQjhCY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2P/wgARCAALABQDASIAAhEBAxEB/8QAGAAAAwEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAEDAgX/xAAVAQEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABAP/aAAwDAQACEAMQAAAB7ioomaE//8QAGRABAAIDAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAQARAhAx/9oACAEBAAEFArgrjWnlDP/EABURAQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAR/9oACAEDAQE/AUf/xAAVEQEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAEf/aAAgBAgEBPwFX/8QAGhAAAgIDAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAEQESEiMv/aAAgBAQAGPwJmyo5bnJ//xAAcEAEAAgEFAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABABExEEFRcYH/2gAIAQEAAT8hHSBXYiFtcXENei9MkCDl3P/aAAwDAQACAAMAAAAQfz//xAAXEQADAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAfAR/9oACAEDAQE/EMHJH//EABURAQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAB/9oACAECAQE/EEP/xAAdEAEBAAEEAwAAAAAAAAAAAAABEQAQITFxQYHB/9oACAEBAAE/EEgQVSX3iYd6ydu8sOB4D6aEejBeWOaz/9k=&apos;); background-size: cover; display: block;&quot;
  &gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;img
        class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-image&quot;
        alt=&quot;The batch layer of Freya&quot;
        title=&quot;The batch layer of Freya&quot;
        src=&quot;/static/31c8e6d965c11e632ba9b164be204fd8/1c72d/1.jpg&quot;
        srcset=&quot;/static/31c8e6d965c11e632ba9b164be204fd8/a80bd/1.jpg 148w,
/static/31c8e6d965c11e632ba9b164be204fd8/1c91a/1.jpg 295w,
/static/31c8e6d965c11e632ba9b164be204fd8/1c72d/1.jpg 590w,
/static/31c8e6d965c11e632ba9b164be204fd8/c84e8/1.jpg 743w&quot;
        sizes=&quot;(max-width: 590px) 100vw, 590px&quot;
        style=&quot;width:100%;height:100%;margin:0;vertical-align:middle;position:absolute;top:0;left:0;&quot;
        loading=&quot;lazy&quot;
      /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The real-time layer of Freya is also master-slave Storm architecture. Master node runs the Zookeeper server, Nimbus, UI and supervisor and the slave nodes act as supervisor nodes. Here is a diagram describing this architecture:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
      class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-wrapper&quot;
      style=&quot;position: relative; display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;  max-width: 590px;&quot;
    &gt;
      &lt;a
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-link&quot;
    href=&quot;/static/9b6ac2c8637e00b6c9cd6f71c75d6b33/3fd11/2.jpg&quot;
    style=&quot;display: block&quot;
    target=&quot;_blank&quot;
    rel=&quot;noopener&quot;
  &gt;
    &lt;span
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-background-image&quot;
    style=&quot;padding-bottom: 51.35135135135135%; position: relative; bottom: 0; left: 0; background-image: url(&apos;data:image/jpeg;base64,/9j/2wBDABALDA4MChAODQ4SERATGCgaGBYWGDEjJR0oOjM9PDkzODdASFxOQERXRTc4UG1RV19iZ2hnPk1xeXBkeFxlZ2P/2wBDARESEhgVGC8aGi9jQjhCY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2P/wgARCAAKABQDASIAAhEBAxEB/8QAGAAAAwEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAECAwX/xAAVAQEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAf/aAAwDAQACEAMQAAAB7s6JJGH/xAAZEAEAAgMAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABETEAAhD/2gAIAQEAAQUCnCXXjRX/xAAUEQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAQ/9oACAEDAQE/AT//xAAUEQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAQ/9oACAECAQE/AT//xAAYEAACAwAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAREgIv/aAAgBAQAGPwI0or//xAAbEAACAgMBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAREhEDFRcf/aAAgBAQABPyGV14M5a4mVycbxU1lH/9oADAMBAAIAAwAAABAvL//EABQRAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABD/2gAIAQMBAT8QP//EABQRAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABD/2gAIAQIBAT8QP//EABwQAQADAAIDAAAAAAAAAAAAAAEAESEQMUGRof/aAAgBAQABPxAVq8MODEIvLZ+ykFvHa7wPTEEFrtJ//9k=&apos;); background-size: cover; display: block;&quot;
  &gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;img
        class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-image&quot;
        alt=&quot;The real-time layer of Freya&quot;
        title=&quot;The real-time layer of Freya&quot;
        src=&quot;/static/9b6ac2c8637e00b6c9cd6f71c75d6b33/1c72d/2.jpg&quot;
        srcset=&quot;/static/9b6ac2c8637e00b6c9cd6f71c75d6b33/a80bd/2.jpg 148w,
/static/9b6ac2c8637e00b6c9cd6f71c75d6b33/1c91a/2.jpg 295w,
/static/9b6ac2c8637e00b6c9cd6f71c75d6b33/1c72d/2.jpg 590w,
/static/9b6ac2c8637e00b6c9cd6f71c75d6b33/3fd11/2.jpg 775w&quot;
        sizes=&quot;(max-width: 590px) 100vw, 590px&quot;
        style=&quot;width:100%;height:100%;margin:0;vertical-align:middle;position:absolute;top:0;left:0;&quot;
        loading=&quot;lazy&quot;
      /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The database gateway is a Node.js app which exposes various API endpoints to query the databases for the result of the job performed on the whole dataset.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
      class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-wrapper&quot;
      style=&quot;position: relative; display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;  max-width: 590px;&quot;
    &gt;
      &lt;a
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-link&quot;
    href=&quot;/static/8ab792a186d108f4bc0290e6b6b1103e/b040c/3.jpg&quot;
    style=&quot;display: block&quot;
    target=&quot;_blank&quot;
    rel=&quot;noopener&quot;
  &gt;
    &lt;span
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-background-image&quot;
    style=&quot;padding-bottom: 34.45945945945946%; position: relative; bottom: 0; left: 0; background-image: url(&apos;data:image/jpeg;base64,/9j/2wBDABALDA4MChAODQ4SERATGCgaGBYWGDEjJR0oOjM9PDkzODdASFxOQERXRTc4UG1RV19iZ2hnPk1xeXBkeFxlZ2P/2wBDARESEhgVGC8aGi9jQjhCY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2P/wgARCAAHABQDASIAAhEBAxEB/8QAFwABAAMAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAECBf/EABUBAQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAB/9oADAMBAAIQAxAAAAHZkSoX/8QAGBABAQADAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAgEDERL/2gAIAQEAAQUCOrcnUIVY/8QAFBEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAEP/aAAgBAwEBPwE//8QAFBEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAEP/aAAgBAgEBPwE//8QAGhAAAQUBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAECESIxYf/aAAgBAQAGPwLpXRHZJ//EABkQAQACAwAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAEAUREhcf/aAAgBAQABPyF8PcbUiLhZxRP/2gAMAwEAAgADAAAAEP8Az//EABURAQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAEQ/9oACAEDAQE/ECf/xAAVEQEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABEP/aAAgBAgEBPxBn/8QAGBABAAMBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAQARQSH/2gAIAQEAAT8QtD04vIpYBTRsV0Bdi6yf/9k=&apos;); background-size: cover; display: block;&quot;
  &gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;img
        class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-image&quot;
        alt=&quot;Database Gateway of Freya&quot;
        title=&quot;Database Gateway of Freya&quot;
        src=&quot;/static/8ab792a186d108f4bc0290e6b6b1103e/1c72d/3.jpg&quot;
        srcset=&quot;/static/8ab792a186d108f4bc0290e6b6b1103e/a80bd/3.jpg 148w,
/static/8ab792a186d108f4bc0290e6b6b1103e/1c91a/3.jpg 295w,
/static/8ab792a186d108f4bc0290e6b6b1103e/1c72d/3.jpg 590w,
/static/8ab792a186d108f4bc0290e6b6b1103e/b040c/3.jpg 844w&quot;
        sizes=&quot;(max-width: 590px) 100vw, 590px&quot;
        style=&quot;width:100%;height:100%;margin:0;vertical-align:middle;position:absolute;top:0;left:0;&quot;
        loading=&quot;lazy&quot;
      /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So overall we have an aggregation of these different components as the final product. Of course, it is not the best solution as it has its own limitations. For example, we have increased the number of point of failures. But given the optimization in terms of time that we are getting here is remarkable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
      class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-wrapper&quot;
      style=&quot;position: relative; display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;  max-width: 590px;&quot;
    &gt;
      &lt;a
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-link&quot;
    href=&quot;/static/b03ddf1b642f6d1440370213464496c8/dde82/4.jpg&quot;
    style=&quot;display: block&quot;
    target=&quot;_blank&quot;
    rel=&quot;noopener&quot;
  &gt;
    &lt;span
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-background-image&quot;
    style=&quot;padding-bottom: 57.432432432432435%; position: relative; bottom: 0; left: 0; background-image: url(&apos;data:image/jpeg;base64,/9j/2wBDABALDA4MChAODQ4SERATGCgaGBYWGDEjJR0oOjM9PDkzODdASFxOQERXRTc4UG1RV19iZ2hnPk1xeXBkeFxlZ2P/2wBDARESEhgVGC8aGi9jQjhCY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2P/wgARCAALABQDASIAAhEBAxEB/8QAFwAAAwEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAECBf/EABQBAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAD/2gAMAwEAAhADEAAAAdynIyg//8QAFxAAAwEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAEhIP/aAAgBAQABBQJVFx//xAAUEQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAQ/9oACAEDAQE/AT//xAAUEQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAQ/9oACAECAQE/AT//xAAXEAADAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAQICEx/9oACAEBAAY/ArBif//EABoQAQEBAQADAAAAAAAAAAAAAAERADEQUfH/2gAIAQEAAT8hs016wTmv00uAGHJ4/9oADAMBAAIAAwAAABCQD//EABQRAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABD/2gAIAQMBAT8QP//EABQRAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABD/2gAIAQIBAT8QP//EABoQAQACAwEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAEAERAxQaH/2gAIAQEAAT8QTJ621CYJoKpt9iHDCKWahMAAANGP/9k=&apos;); background-size: cover; display: block;&quot;
  &gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;img
        class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-image&quot;
        alt=&quot;Complete architecture of Freya&quot;
        title=&quot;Complete architecture of Freya&quot;
        src=&quot;/static/b03ddf1b642f6d1440370213464496c8/1c72d/4.jpg&quot;
        srcset=&quot;/static/b03ddf1b642f6d1440370213464496c8/a80bd/4.jpg 148w,
/static/b03ddf1b642f6d1440370213464496c8/1c91a/4.jpg 295w,
/static/b03ddf1b642f6d1440370213464496c8/1c72d/4.jpg 590w,
/static/b03ddf1b642f6d1440370213464496c8/a8a14/4.jpg 885w,
/static/b03ddf1b642f6d1440370213464496c8/dde82/4.jpg 910w&quot;
        sizes=&quot;(max-width: 590px) 100vw, 590px&quot;
        style=&quot;width:100%;height:100%;margin:0;vertical-align:middle;position:absolute;top:0;left:0;&quot;
        loading=&quot;lazy&quot;
      /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Merits and shortcomings of Freya&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some good things about Freya:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Since the input data is never modified, it makes huge map reduce jobs tractable. The jobs are easy to control and each stage in the job can be debugged easily.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The code keeps changing. The jobs keep changing. It may be because of bugs or requirement changes or other reasons. But Freya(since it is based on top of LA) is resilient to this change. Batch processing deals with this problem easily by re-computing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are some shortcomings as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The duplicative development effort in building hot(real-time) and cold(offline) paths of their processing pipeline. The additional overhead of reprocessing the data in the batch layer which were processed in the stream layer. The overhead of merging the results of both layer also counts as developer overhead.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Maintaining the code that produces the same result in every complex distributed framework. There are many points of failures.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Operational overhead is high for maintaining, running and debugging two systems simultaneously.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So why use Freya depends on the use case. In our case, lambda architecture is best-fit considering the academic use cases. So operational overhead is considerably low. Also, the nodes are physically located in one place. So it’s easy to debug and the infrastructure is less network error prone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have tried to achieve automation to the greatest extent possible. With Freya, your in-house LA will be up and running within minutes ✌️. Below is a demo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-resp-iframe-wrapper&quot; style=&quot;padding-bottom: 56.25%; position: relative; height: 0; overflow: hidden; margin-bottom: 1.0725rem&quot; &gt; &lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/ccbEO9abQpw&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen style=&quot; position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; &quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt; &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Setting up Freya&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The code for Freya is on &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/rashi-sahu/Freya&quot;&gt;Github&lt;/a&gt;. This project would not have been successful without the contributions of my project partner &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/rashi-sahu&quot;&gt;Rashi&lt;/a&gt; and guidance of our mentor &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/sumit-kalra-97a06933/&quot;&gt;Dr Sumit Kalra&lt;/a&gt;. I am thankful to them for their inputs. We are thinking of adding more features and bringing it to the usage of the common.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks for reading !!! Feel free to connect with me on &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/whoAbhishekSah&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt; for any conversations.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[JSON vs Protocol Buffer]]></title><description><![CDATA[Introduction: Data is everywhere. Computer programs perform different operations on the data to make meaning out of them. There may be a…]]></description><link>http://abhisheksah.xyz/JSON-vs-Protocol-buffer/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">http://abhisheksah.xyz/JSON-vs-Protocol-buffer/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 09 Jun 2018 22:12:03 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;h4&gt;Introduction:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Data is everywhere. Computer programs perform different operations on the data to make meaning out of them. There may be a need of data exchange among programs as well. For ex. say a mobile app(client) may ask data from an API endpoint(server) or a web server may query a database for data etc. This article is about the data exchange part.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So how can a program written in a language (say Ruby) exchange data with another program written in language (say JavaScript) over a network. We need some uniform format for data which all languages are compatible with, which all language can easily understand and parse efficiently in their data structures. We first encode the raw data in that format and serialize it, send it over the network or make it available to other programs over a network.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;JSON&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;JSON is one such format. JSON stands for Javascript Object Notation. It’s a lightweight data interchange format. A JSON object is typically used to contain some data in key/value format. It looks like a string wrapped in curly braces with colons between the names and values, and commas between the values and names. See example below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;json&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;language-json&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-json&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token property&quot;&gt;&quot;id&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&quot;2&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token property&quot;&gt;&quot;name&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&quot;Abhishek&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token property&quot;&gt;&quot;message&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&quot;Read a book&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token property&quot;&gt;&quot;time&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&quot;2200&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here &lt;em&gt;id&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;name&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;message&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;time&lt;/em&gt; are the keys with values &lt;em&gt;2&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Abhishek&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Read a book&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;2200&lt;/em&gt; respectively. It is analogous to hash(map). The order in which these keys appear don’t matter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A JSON Array is a collection of JSON objects wrapped in &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;[ ]&lt;/code&gt; separated by a comma. It is analogous to array. The order matters here. See example below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;json&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;language-json&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-json&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token property&quot;&gt;&quot;id&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&quot;2&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token property&quot;&gt;&quot;name&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&quot;Abhishek&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token property&quot;&gt;&quot;message&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&quot;Read a book&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token property&quot;&gt;&quot;time&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&quot;2200&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token property&quot;&gt;&quot;id&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&quot;3&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token property&quot;&gt;&quot;name&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&quot;Uneet&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token property&quot;&gt;&quot;message&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&quot;Order Lunch&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token property&quot;&gt;&quot;time&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&quot;1400&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The JSON object and JSON arrays can be nested in each other as well. See example below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;json&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;language-json&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-json&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token property&quot;&gt;&quot;room&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&quot;G75&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token property&quot;&gt;&quot;data&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token property&quot;&gt;&quot;id&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&quot;2&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token property&quot;&gt;&quot;name&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&quot;Abhishek&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token property&quot;&gt;&quot;id&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&quot;3&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token property&quot;&gt;&quot;name&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&quot;Uneet&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;JSON supports few basic data types.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Numbers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;String&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Boolean&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Array(Ordered list)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Object (Unordered list)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now we know how we can represent our data in JSON. We can encode our data in our program in JSON format. Some other program may ask for this data and decode it. Mostly all programming languages now-a-days have methods in their standard libraries which perform encoding and decoding of the data with just one line of code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Protocol Buffer&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Protocol Buffer is another such data-interchange format invented by Google. It is smaller, faster, and simpler than JSON and other data formats out there. JSON is a simple method to represent data. Protocol buffer introduces a schema in the data. For this we first define a (.proto) file. It contains how we want to structure our data. The first JSON object example that I stated earlier, can be given a structure in protocol buffer as given below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;java&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;language-java&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-java&quot;&gt;message &lt;span class=&quot;token class-name&quot;&gt;Todo&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
optional int32 id &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
 required string name &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
 required string message &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
 required google&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;protobuf&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token class-name&quot;&gt;Timestamp&lt;/span&gt; time &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;4&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that how we can specify data types (int32, int64, string, timestamp etc), the data labels (optional, required) in our .proto file. Each field has a unique tag. The 1, 2, 3 and 4 in the RHS are the tags to fields. The numbered tags are used to match fields when serializing and deserializing the data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This gives much more flexibility to extract meaning out of data in an easy manner as compared to JSON. This is a pretty simple example of a proto file. Protocol Buffer have support for namespaces, enumerations as well. After defining the structure, you run the protocol buffer compiler for your application’s language on your (.proto) file to generate data access classes. They will give you simple accessor function for each field.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;JSON specifies the key(field) in every object which increases the data size. Protocol buffer uses the tags to identify fields. So it’s memory efficient than JSON.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A schema is very useful in maintaining the structure of data. It counters many inconsistencies that may get introduced if structure was not defined explicitly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Protocol Buffers have several more advantages over JSON. You can add new fields without breaking anything. Old binaries simply ignore the new field when parsing. This is called backward compatibility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I highly recommend you to see the code samples on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://developers.google.com/protocol-buffers/&quot;&gt;official documentation&lt;/a&gt; of Protocol Buffers. This makes concepts really clear via code samples and working examples in many languages.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item></channel></rss>